<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of the assault committed vpon the person of the most noble prince, William Prince of Orange, Countie of Nassau, Marquesse de la Vere &amp;c. by Iohn Iauregui Spaniarde With the true copies of the writings, examinations, depositions, and letters of sundrie offenders in that vile and diuelish atempte. Faithfullye translated out of the Frenche copie printed at Antwerp by Christopher Plantin. Anno 1582.</title>
            <author>Jáuregui y Aguilar, Juan de, 1583-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837661</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1999</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1999)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1016:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of the assault committed vpon the person of the most noble prince, William Prince of Orange, Countie of Nassau, Marquesse de la Vere &amp;c. by Iohn Iauregui Spaniarde With the true copies of the writings, examinations, depositions, and letters of sundrie offenders in that vile and diuelish atempte. Faithfullye translated out of the Frenche copie printed at Antwerp by Christopher Plantin. Anno 1582.</title>
                  <author>Jáuregui y Aguilar, Juan de, 1583-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[by H. Bynneman] for Thomas Charde and William Broome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Iohn Iauregui Spaniarde = Juan de Jáuregui y Aguilar.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]²  A-L⁴ M¹.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  I, --  Prince of Orange, 1533-1584 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:1"/>
            <p>A TRVE DISCOVRSE OF THE ASSAVLT COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITTED VPON THE PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the moſt noble Prince, <hi>William Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>Countie of</hi> Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau, Marqueſſe de la Vere &amp;c. by Iohn Iauregui Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niarde.</p>
            <p>With the true Copies of the writings, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations, Depoſitions, and Letters of ſundrie offenders in that vile and diueliſh attempte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfullye tranſlated out of the frenche Copie prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Antwerp by Chriſtopher Plantin. Anno.</hi> 1582.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>CERVA CHARISSIMA ET GRATISSIMVS HINNVLVS PRO: 5</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Charde and William Broome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:2"/>
            <head>¶To the Reader, Grace and Peace from God. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here (good Chriſtian Reader) a true narration, of that horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble facte, committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that godlye and great perſon, my Lorde the Prince of Orange, together with the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, depoſitions, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and letters of ſundrie heinous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders in this wicked &amp; cruel deede: ſome of which are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die executed, thankes be to God for ſuch Iuſtice; the other, howſoeuer they are eſcaped, as yet free from the puniſhment of men, haue, without vnfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, greater iudgements laide vp in ſtore for them, with the Lord, who will plentifullie puniſhe ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and traiterous dealing. Concerning the credit and truth of this diſcourſe, it is ſo plaine and ſufficient, that neither all the Spaniardes in the worlde, nor all their fauourites whatſoeuer or whereſoeuer, ſhal be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iuſtlie any maner of way, to impugne or diſgrace the ſame. The blow was giuen the greater is the ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:3"/>
and the good Prince grieuouſlie wounded, the more is the pitie, if the Lord had otherwiſe ſeene it good. A Spaniarde was the firſt broacher of it, by publiſhing that horrible proſcription which by the Princes Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie is fullie aunſwered, both to the great ſhame and diſcredite of ſome, &amp; alſo to the wonderfull glorie and commendation of that good Prince. And as a Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde deuiſed it,<note place="margin">I meane the death of the partie, whiche alſo I praye GOD they maye long want, &amp; the church enioie his life, for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods glory in the ſame.</note> and a Spaniarde performed it, ſundrie of that proude and cruell nation, being combined and comperted in it, as ſome of their own confeſsions, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before Gods Magiſtrates, doe plainlie witneſſe it, whereby they haue bewraied their miſchieuous mindes, though (thankes be to God for it) they haue hitherto miſſed of their purpoſe: ſo I muſt needes ſaie, that if anie ſhould bee ſo ſhameleſſe as to denie it, or ſo beaſtlie as to blanche it, or iuſtifie it (as I feare me ſome, and that no ſmall ſome are) I would no more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with ſuche, than with thoſe, that would denie the Sunne to ſhine at noone daies. If there be none ſuche amongſte vs, then there is no hurt done. But if they be here, or elſe where in the world (as Fraunce, Scotlande, and Flaunders, now at the laſt, haue yeelded vs ſome feareful examples) and it is to be thought, that we haue too too manie, of that ſame Ieſuiticall ſect, who bluſh not, both to reaſon too and fro, concerning ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and to labour the attempting thereof (as wee haue had of late proofe ſufficient) and that not to the maiming of meane men, but to the hurting of the higheſt (whome I beſeeche God in mercie long to preſerue) then I would haue ſuch to know and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that to them it is that I ſpeake, not in heate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their perſons, or to aggrauate their offences which are ſo grieuous, as no weight of wordes, cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1999:3"/>
make them more heinous, but in the ſincere zeale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God in the dutifull reuerence of hir Maieſtie, in ſound affection to the common wealth and countrie, and in loue vnfeigned towards them, wiſhing from my heart their heartie conuerſion, if they appertaine to God, or elſe their vtter and ſpeedie confuſion (ſpeciallie if they be ſuch as the Lord hath ſealed vp againſte the daye of his wrath) for their ſtubbornneſſe in hereſies, touching matters of faith, and their practiſes againſte the beſt in matters of eſtate: but inough of this matter at this time. The principall point, that I would haue the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reader (of what ſtate or condition ſoeuer he be) to regard in this narration is, to labour to make it profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to himſelfe, that as generally it may inſtruct all, not to beleeue euery flying tale, but to let go running rumours and reportes, and withall earneſtly to pray to God for all his children (my meaning is while they are aliue) that be ſo ouertaken, and namely for this good Prince his faithfull ſeruaunt, that according to Gods good pleaſure, he and they all whatſoeuer in the like daungers, may recouer their wounds, and learne more Chriſtian care and godlie wiſedome in time hereafter to come: ſo particularlie, it may teach euery one, euen the hihheſt fitſt, and namely this, whome it doth moſte chiefly concerne, that ſeeing that for their well doing, the enemies meane ſuch miſchiefes againſt them, they may carefully looke vnto themſelues, that they be not ſurpriſed with ſuch popiſh practiſes, being alwayes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie circumſpect whome they admit to their preſence and ſpeeche, and ſo preuent ſuch feareful daungers: and the loweſt next, to pray to the Lord, as for themſelues, that they be not intrapped, ſo chiefly for theſe that be their ſuperiors (becauſe if the head or principall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb facs="tcp:1999:4"/>
be ſtroken, the whole bodie is in danger of death and deſtruction) that they may liue long and gouerne alſo, in truth, peace and godlineſſe, without any ſuche wicked attempt, to be either deuiſed or performed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte them or any of them: which God graunt, as to all nations profeſsing his word and truth, ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the nation and countrie of Englande, euen for his crucified Chriſtes ſake: that ſo the lande may flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, by the long life and proſperous raigne, of theſe that bee in authoritie, and the Church increaſe, by the pure doctrine of the Goſpell alreadie eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and by the planting of Gods holye Diſcipline. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:4"/>
            <head>A briefe diſcourſe of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault committed vpon the perſon of the moſt noble Prince, WILLIAM Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Countie of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau, Marques de la Vere &amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Iohn Iauregui</hi> a Spaniard.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> after he had heard the ſermon in the Church on Sonday the xviij. day of March <hi>1582.</hi> repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his houſe, in the place where ſometime the Caſtel of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> ſtoode, accompanied with manye Lords and Gentlemen, of whom ſome dined with him. Immediatelie after he had dined openly (as he was wont) in the great Hall of the ſayd houſe, my Lordes the Counties <hi>de Laual, de Hohenlo,</hi> my Lords his children, and two of his nephewes, children of my Lorde the Countie <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> the Lords of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuet, des Pruneaux,</hi> and other gentlemen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying
<pb facs="tcp:1999:5"/>
him The dinner was paſſed &amp; ſpent with many honeſt communications &amp; ſpéeches, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt all others, was ſome ſpéeche had of the cruelties committed by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes</hi> in theſe low Countries. A little after dinner, the ſayde Prince repayred into his withdrawing chamber, intending to go into his bedde Chamber with the ſayd Lords and gentlemen, and as he paſſed by, ſhewed them a péece of tapiſtrie, wherein were liuelye ſet forth the Spaniſh ſouldiours. At the ſayd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, a yong man of low ſtature ſhot at the ſayd Prince with a dagge, charged with one only pellet, the ſhot wherof hit him vnder the right eare, &amp; paſſed through the pallet of his mouth and came forth at his left chéeke, néere vnto his vpper iaw bone: the ſaide Lorde (as ſince he hath ſaid many times) did not know what it was, but thought that ſome parte of the houſe had fallen, for he felt not himſelf to be ſtricken: notwithſtanding his ſighte was a little while dazeled. Immediatelye ſome of the Lords &amp; gentlemen then next at hand, ſtroke the ſaid yong man twice or thrice into the bodie with their ſwordes, and ſo the ſaide Princes garde drawing nigh, made an ende of him with their Haulberds. In the meane
<pb facs="tcp:1999:5"/>
time the ſayd Prince being aduertiſed what had happened, &amp; the rather by féeling the fyre that had taken hold of his haire, and hearing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noiſe about the murderer, cried out, kil him not, I forgiue him my death: and ſo turning to ſundrie French Lords, ſaid vnto them: O how faithfull a ſeruaunt doeth his highneſſe loſe and ſo was ſtraight ledde betwéene two (that helde him vp by the armes) into his chamber: for he coulde goe, and fell not with the blow. The brute hereof wente preſentlye ouer all the towne, which brought moſt men into a maze, by reaſon of ſo ſodaine and vnlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for a matter, and that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of ſuch a one, as among all men was holden &amp; repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a deliuerer of the Countrie, further, becauſe the murderer was preſently dead, all men iudged that the way to verifie and iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the facte, was quite ſhut vp. Many and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe were the ſpéeches hereof: ſome through ſuſpition accuſing others, and few hitting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the truth and attributing the leaſt to them who were the very authours indéede: ſo as if ſuche a déede had bene committed in manye townes where the people haue the bridle at libertie, and may at their pleaſure run from place to place, it had bene likelie that ſome
<pb facs="tcp:1999:6"/>
great miſchief and inconuenience might haue enſued: But in the town of <hi>Antwerp</hi> (ſuch is the order and obedience that all men do yéeld to their Magiſtrates, Coronels &amp; Captayns) immediately al the citizens withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to their Enſignes ech one in his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the chaines being drawne, &amp; the body of the gard filled, there was no way lefte for any to departe from his garde but the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. My Lord the Duke of <hi>Brabant</hi> was ſpéedily aduertiſed of this miſhappe, and bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the firſt certifyed of no other tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, he was greatly aſtonied, and ſighing verye déepely, complained to himſelf of the extreme loſſe which thereby he ſuſtained: repeating oftentimes, that if the king his owne father had bene aliue againe, he could not haue bene more ſorie for his death, than for the death of the ſaid Prince: where on the other ſide the Prince bewayled him no leſſe, rehearſing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes theſe wordes: Alas poore Prince, alas poore Prince, what pains muſt thou yet take? Whiles moſt part of his ſeruants that were preſent, as alſo thoſe which at the brute of the newes were come in, employed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about the ſaid L Princes perſon, his ſonne the Earle <hi>Maurice,</hi> notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:1999:6"/>
his heauie mourning, departed not from the dead corps which he cauſed to be ſearched: &amp; firſt they light vpon the dag which was falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of his hande, that cauſed them to thinke that he had no meanes to vſe a dagger, which they found naked in his bréeches. In the meane ſeaſon the Earle of <hi>Hohenlo,</hi> for feare of further inconuenience, cauſing the ſayd Princes gard and diuerſe Gentlemen to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, ſeaſed vpon the doores of the houſe, ſo to kéepe all ſuche as were not verye well knowne, from comming in or going forth. The dead corps being further ſearched, they found about him certaine papers and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets which were deliuered to the ſaid Erle <hi>Maurice,</hi> the which at that inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t finding one of the ſeruants of my Lord his father ſhewed him the ſaid Papers, and wéeping ſaide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked wretch had about him: who anſwered him, my Lord be not diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, God is mightie and able to preſerue my Lord your father, but kéepe theſe papers wel, for we are greatly troubled about diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering ſomewhat of this curſed wretche: for otherwiſe in this Town we ſhal incur great peril. To the which he did replie, alas I am afrayde leaſt here be ſome other villaine that
<pb facs="tcp:1999:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may take them from me, this yong Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rather moued to ſay ſo, becauſe there went a ſpeeche through the Hall, giuen foorth by ſome, that thoſe which had killed the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, were partakers of the fact, and that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be aſſured of it, ſo that the daunger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to fall likewiſe vpon the beſt friendes of the ſaid Lord Prince, and vppon his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold. Vpon this talke of the ſayd yong Erle, the ſaid ſeruaunt tooke him vnder his Cloke, and ſaid vnto him, my Lord go with me, and I will lay your Papers in ſafetie, whiche hée did, bringing him into the roofe of the houſe, where committing the ſaid papers to ſafe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, he perceiued that they were written in Spaniſh, wherefore he ſaid to the Earle, My Lord, there is no danger to be feared on your part, returne and cauſe further ſearche to bée made: as for me. I go to my Lord: which was done. Then the ſaid ſeruant began to certifie euery one, that it was a <hi>Spaniarde,</hi> and that men ſhould leaue the miſſconceiued ſuſpition which they had. A while after returned the ſayd yong Earle, bringing mo Papers, Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; an <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> with a gréene wax Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, &amp; two pieces of ſkin, like vnto a beauers: which occaſioned many to be of opinion that
<pb facs="tcp:1999:7"/>
he had about him ſome Toades and enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The ſaide ſeruant began to reade the firſt Papers: whiche he founde to be, partlye praiers, and partly vowes, and then he brake the couer of a packet of letters, and found that it was written in Spaniſh, by one Spaniard to another, of the whiche he did certifie euerie man, but would not open the reſt alone A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after came the Lord <hi>de S. Aldegonde,</hi> who had alreadie bene with his highneſſe, and being returned, ſaide to the ſame ſeruant, we muſt take aduiſe what is to be done, for there is great trouble in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Town: whervnto he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, my Lord, if it pleaſe you, let vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw our ſelues for a while to communicate therof, I thinke you ſhal finde counſell rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: and then they wente by themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great preaſſe of people that was about them, and the ſaide Lord did open the reſt of the ſaide packet, in which were founde two letters of exchaunge, the one of <hi>2000.</hi> crownes, and the other of <hi>877.</hi> with let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of aduice, all in Spaniſh, and by Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards: the bookes were of ſeruices to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at certain ſet hours: alſo one Ieſuits Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme &amp; a paire of tables written from one ende to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. Then praiſing God, that had
<pb facs="tcp:1999:8"/>
giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord <hi>de S. Aldegonde,</hi> reſolued to go ſtraight to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Town houſe, &amp; paſſing by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gard, to aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it was done be <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whiche he did hope to verifie: and would carrie with him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writing tables and the moſt parte of the writings: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing others to go to his highnes with the other part, to aduertiſe him, and not to depart from his perſon: which was done. In paſſing by, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Lorde of <hi>Saint Aldegonde</hi> went alſo in to his highneſſe, &amp; ſhewed him the ſayde Papers. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean time was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt dreſſing. And the Prince was layde in his bedde, and afterward ſuch as were next about him and moſt ſkilfull, began to conceiue ſome ſparke of hope, by reaſon he had his ſight and ſpake well, eſpecially becauſe his vnderſtanding &amp; iudgement was very certaine, alſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forbidden much ſpeech, he wrote ſtedfaſt and quicke. While theſe things were in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there came in one of the Captaines of the towne, named <hi>Lion Petit,</hi> demaunding whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were aliue or deade, who, when the ſaid ſeruant requeſted him to let the ſayde L. Prince take his reſt for that time, affirming that he hoped of his recouerie, anſwered that the people would neuer be content vnleſſe he
<pb facs="tcp:1999:8"/>
aſſured them that hée had ſéene him: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he was cauſed to enter in: then after ſome ſpéeches, demaunding what it pleaſed the L. Prince to commaund him, he ſaide: Commend me hartily to the people, and will them not to trouble themſelues, &amp; if it pleaſe God to take me to him ſelfe, that they obey &amp; faithfully ſerue this prince, for I know none in the worlde better or more méete for them. His highneſſe hauing ſéene the letters of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge and other the writings brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, commended them to <hi>Martini</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder of the town, who then was with him, to cary them to the Magiſtrate of the towne, and to examine thoſe to whome the letters of Exchaunge were directed: In the meane time hauing aſſembled the counſel of Eſtate, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched a Commiſſion directed vnto the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Eſtates, the counſell of Eſtate, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the towne, the Coronells, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; Wardens of occupations, with all diligence to procéede, commaunding all men vnder paine of death to declare what they knewe concerning the ſayd Murderer. Nowe had the Magiſtrate in the meane time (who already had begun to procéede herein, and by the ſayd papers and writing tables had found
<pb facs="tcp:1999:9"/>
that the Murtherer was of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> named <hi>Iaſper d'Anaſtro</hi>) taken order that all that were in the ſayd houſe ſhould be committed to priſon, which was done. But they found that the ſayd <hi>Anaſtro</hi> himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the tueſday before toward <hi>Bruges</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were the Coronels and Captaines aduertiſed by the Magiſtrate, alſo all the Inhabitants by their Gouernours, that all this webbe was wouen by the <hi>Spanyards:</hi> whervpon the whole towne grew to quietneſſe, remainyng neuertheleſſe in armes, for the aſſiſtance of iuſtice. At the firſt examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Antony Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero</hi> they could not finde any great matter, but this onely, that they knewe the Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers perſon: Howbeit for that he confeſſed that the ſame day Maſſe had bene celebrated ſecretly in the ſayd <hi>Anaſtro</hi> his houſe, at all aduentures vpon ſuſpition they apprehended one <hi>Antony Timmerman,</hi> of the order of the white Friers. Neuertheleſſe it was decréed, that the Murderers body ſhould be ſet vpon a ſcaffold in the towne to ſhew it to the people, to the end to know it, which thing was done: but ſo ſoone as he was ſéene in the great market place, euery one knew it preſently to be the body of <hi>Iohn Iauregui</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:1999:9"/>
ſeruant of <hi>Iaſper Anaſtro:</hi> yea the ſayde <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero</hi> ſéeing him dead, knew him. The next morning the xix. of March, as all the gates of the towne of <hi>Antwerp</hi> were diligently kept, in the morning the Poſt of <hi>Bruges</hi> arriued, who hauing ſhewed his letters to the Garde of the Riuer gate, there were found letters of the ſayd <hi>Anaſtro</hi> directed to <hi>Venero,</hi> which were caried to his highneſſe and to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of the towne. Further, the Magiſtrate appointed, that the ſame day the Murtherers body ſhould be quartered, and his head ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bulwarke toward <hi>Ril,</hi> and his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vpon the foure principall gates, which was done. The next day his highneſſe and the Counſell of eſtate decréed, that throughout all the Churches there ſhould be extraordinarie prayers vnto God for the health of the ſayde L. Prince. Alſo by the Magiſtrate of the towne his apointment, the next Wedneſday being the <hi>21.</hi> of the ſayd Moneth, was by tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet proclaimed throughout the towne a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall faſt, with common prayers: alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement was giuen that euery man ſhould that day leaue all worke, to the ende to attend faſting and prayer. <hi>Annaſtro</hi> his letters were ſhewed to <hi>Venero,</hi> who ſéeing
<pb facs="tcp:1999:10"/>
him ſelfe thereby confounded and conuicted, and being, as by his confeſſion it appeareth, admoniſhed by one of the Coronels &amp; others, required paper and inke, and with his owne hand wrote and ſigned his ſecond confeſſion. The Prince thinking the houre of his deceaſe to drawe neare, diſpatched the L. <hi>S. Alde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonde</hi> with letters directed to the generall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, wherein, as his laſt counſel, he wiſhed them to perſiſt in his highneſſe obedience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring vnto them that he iudged him to be the onely Prince that was moſt fit for them, according to the tenure whereof, the ſayde Lordes ſent their Deputies to his highneſſe, to aduertiſe him of their faithfull affection. Vpon wedneſday following was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſt with extraordinary prayers celebrated, and that with ſuch multitude and concourſe of people, in all the Churches of both languages, as time out of mind the like numbers of people haue not bene ſéene in the Churches of <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp,</hi> neither ſo many wéeping eyes. Howbeit for that the Phiſitions and Surgeons began to conceiue ſome hope of the recouerie of the ſayde Prince, the prayers were partely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with thankes giuings for this good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with humble ſupplication, that it might
<pb facs="tcp:1999:10"/>
pleaſe God to accompliſh his health. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the ſayde L. Princes perſon to drawe to amendment, and dayly did his highneſſe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully viſit him, who ſéemed, and in déede did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake great care for him, as likewiſe the L. Prince did for him, vppon euerye occaſion commending his ſeruice. On the other ſide, the Magiſtrate was as diligent in procéeding againſt the offendors: ſo as finally he attey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the truth of the whole matter, as it wil appeare in the depoſitions of the ſayd offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors. But the L. Prince hearing that they purpoſed to procéede to definitiue ſentence, did by writing expreſlye commaund the L. of <hi>S. Aldegonde,</hi> to requeſt the Magiſtrate to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with the eaſieſt death that might be: which was done: for by the Magiſtrates ſentence the wedneſday <hi>28.</hi> of the ſayd moneth they were ſet at a ſtake vpon a ſcaffold in the middeſt of the great market, ouer againſt the towne houſe, and by the hangman ſtrangled, their bodies quartered, and hanged ouer the chiefe gates of the towne, and their heades pitched vppon two of the great bulwarkes which heretofore were part of the caſtle. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony Timmerman</hi> the white Frier the ſame day exhibited his ſecond confeſſion, wherein he acknowledged that he had bene of opinion
<pb facs="tcp:1999:11"/>
that the ſayd <hi>Iaregui</hi> might with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience execute the ſayd enterpriſe: but that nowe being better inſtructed by ſuch good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions as had bene giuen him, he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that he had erred, &amp; therefore beſought the Lords of Iuſtice not to forget his ſayd prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, if euer this proceſſe were publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Within few dayes after the ſayd executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his highneſſe receiued from ſundry places letters which the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the townes, wherein he endeuored to perſwade them to withdraw them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his obedience, laying his foundation vppon the death of the ſayd L. Prince, wherevpon the ſayde townes beſought his highneſſe of counſaile. Theſe were the townes: <hi>Bruſſels, Gaunt, Bridges, Malines, Ipres, Audernarde, Dunkirk, Berghe</hi> and ſundry others. Finally the towne of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> alſo receiued the like letters. <hi>Annaſtro</hi> alſo ſent letters to the towne of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> tending to the ſame ende, which <hi>Venero</hi> his depoſition doth containe: ſo that he wrote to all places where he had any acceſſe. All the ſayd letters, as well from the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> as from <hi>Annaſtro</hi> were grounded vpon the aſſurance which they had conceiued of the death of the ſayd L. Prince,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:11"/>
whom God hath hitherto neuertheleſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and will ſtill of his mercie kéepe and preſerue, if he pleaſe.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Hereafter followe:</head>
               <item>The copies of the writings found about the murderer.</item>
               <item>The depoſitions of the Offendors.</item>
               <item>The letters of Annaſtro and the Prince of Parma.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="writings">
            <head>The copies of the Writings founde about the Murtherer.</head>
            <div n="1" type="original">
               <head>IESV CHRISTO NVESTRO Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or, y la Virge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſancta a Maria nueſtra Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora ſean en mi ayuda en eſta reſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hecha para ſu ſanctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo ſeruicio.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>VE ſu Magistad tiene dada esta orden por el amor que tiene à estos Flamencos, y por librarlos de las op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions en que estan.</p>
               <p>Si esto ſe haze, recibira el Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or à este pueblo en miſericordia, y hara con el las capitulaciones en toda ventaja d'ellos.</p>
               <p>Offreſcer les he, que dentro de ocho dias que ſe haga, los vendra a tomar a miſericordia, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante que al que hiziere eſte hecho, le traten bien
<pb facs="tcp:1999:12"/>
que ſera ganancia della villa hazerlo aſsi, y per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donarle la vida, pues la ha empleada tan en ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicio de Dios, y de ſu Ygleſia, y de ſu Rey, y en hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ra de toda ſu nacion: y el que me regalare y trata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re bien, ſe lo pagara ſu Magestad ſu muy cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plidamente. Perſuaderlos que ſe ſuffran, y tengan paciencia quatra o ſeys dias, hasta que ſe le paſſe la alteracion, que despues todo ſe hara tan a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tento de la Villa, como nunca ellos pudieren deſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar. Yo ruego a estos ſen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ores, que miren lo que ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen en tratarme bien porque en hazar lo que he hecho, todas las naciones lo attribuyran a virtud, y nobleza de my nacion. Y pues a qui ſon todos tan virtuoſos, tengan attencion a tratarme bien, haſta tomar mis confeſſiones muy d'espacio, y por ſu orden. Y ſobre todo, yo me encomiendo en la miſericordia de Dios.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="translation">
               <head>IESVS CHRIST OVR LORDE, and the holie Virgin S. Marie our Ladie, aſsiſt mee in this my determination, which I haue vndertaken for his moſt holie ſeruice.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Royall Maieſtie hathe ſette downe this order for the loue he beareth to theſe Flemings, and to deliuer them from the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb facs="tcp:1999:12"/>
wherein they are.</p>
               <p>This being accompliſhed, the Lorde wil receiue theſe people to mercie, and he will graunt them articles tending to their vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt aduantage.</p>
               <p>I will promiſe them, that within eighte dayes after the déede, they ſhal be receiued into fauour, conditionally, that they do wel entreate him that ſhall haue done this déed. That the towne ſhall reape commoditie by ſo doing, alſo to pardon him his life, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering he hath ſo employed it in the ſeruice of God, of the Church, and of his King, and to the honour of his whole nation: and hys Maieſtie will moſt liberally rewarde anye that ſhall furniſhe him of things requiſite, and wel entreate him.</p>
               <p>They muſte bée perſwaded patiently to beare for foure or ſixe dayes, vntil thys al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration be ouer: whiche being paſte, all thinges ſhall be ordered to as great conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Towne, as themſelues could euer wiſhe.</p>
               <p>I beſéeche theſe Lordes well to weigh what they doe in wel vſing of mée: becauſe that, accompliſhing this déede that I haue
<pb facs="tcp:1999:13"/>
done, all nations will attribute it to the vertue and nobilitie of my Countrey.</p>
               <p>In ſo muche therefore, as all men here bée ſo vertuous, they muſte determine, wel to entreate mée, yea, ſo farre foorth, as at leyſure, and as order requyreth, to take my confeſſions. And aboue all thinges, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to the mercie of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="original">
               <head>IESVS MARIA.</head>
               <p>AVos Redemptory Saluado del mundo, Cria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor del cielo y de la tierra, Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſus Christo, ſiendo ſeruido concederme esta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoria a mi todo miſero, muy infelice peccador, y vuestro ſieruo, por a quellas precioſiſſimas cinco llagas y la precioſiſſima corona de ſpinas y los vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros precioſiſſimos grandiſſimos trabaios, angusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, arrastradas, bofetadas, maldezires: e hiel y vinagre ſobre aquello beuiſtes, vos todo poderoſo Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo Redemptor y Saluador del mundo, Criador del cielo y de la tierra, todo por ſaluar a los peccadores del mundo, y a mi to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do muy infelice peccador: y como a talos ſupplico muy humilmente ſeays ſeruido concederme eſta victoria contra eſte Pagano, Violador de vuestro
<pb facs="tcp:1999:13"/>
Templo diuino, Ruina de vnestra religion, ſancta catholica y Romana y el que es occaſion de tanto deſſaſſoſſrego a la vuestra Christiandad, y pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia que no attiende ſino en ſuſtentar maldades, vellaquerias y ruynas. O todo poderoſo Senor Dios Ieſu Christo Redemptor y Saluador del mundo, Criador del cielo y de la tierra a vos os ſupplico muy humilmente ſeays ſeruido no permitir que e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte maluado vſe de mas ruinas, y conceder a mi muy indigno peccador la gracia, animo y valor, paraque deſpues de las vueſtras precioſiſſimas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos pueda ſer acabado por mi. De manera que ninguno de quien yo voy vencerle, despues de vos Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo Redemptor y Saluador del mundo, Criador del cielo y de la tierra pueda auer poder contra mi. Pero despues ſiendo vos al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimo Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptor y Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uador del mundo Criador del cielo y de la tierra ſiendo ſeruido de que yo dexe aqui eſta miſerable vida, ſoy muy contento ſe a aſſi, y ſiempre como vos Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Dios fueredes ſeruido. Y aſſi os ſuplico de todo coraçon todo poderoſo Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo, por a quella vuestra precioſiſſima paſſion ſeays ſeruido concederme constancia y pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencia, paraque yo miſero muy infelice peccador pueda ſobrelleuar y ſuffrir qualquier genero de
<pb facs="tcp:1999:14"/>
pena que me dieren, que a todo (como ſoy obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do) prestare muy humilde cora on, ſiendo vos to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do poderoſo Redemptor y Saluador del mundo Criador del cielo y de la tierra ſeruido.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="translation">
               <head>IESVS MARIA.</head>
               <p>TO thée Redéemer and Sauiour of the worlde, creator of heauen and earth, Lord God, Ieſus Chriſte: If it pleaſe thée to graunte this victorie vnto me moſte mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretched ſinner, and thy ſeruaunt, for the loue of thy fiue moſt pretious woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; thy moſte pretious crowne of thorns, and thy moſt pretious greuous labours, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes, torments, ſtripes, and iniuries, and the gall and vineger, which beſides all thys thou diddeſt drinke, euen thou the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lorde God, Ieſus Chriſte, the redéemer and ſauiour of the world, the creator of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and al to ſaue the ſinners of this world, and among the reſt, me, the moſt vnhappie ſinner: and as ſuche a one I doe moſte humbly beſéeche thée, that it maye pleaſe thée, to grant me this victory againſt this heathen, defiler of thy holy Temple,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:14"/>
and ſubuerter of thy holy catholik Romane religion, who is the cauſe of ſo many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiets throughout thy Chriſtendome, and ſuche a peſtilence, as is buſied onely in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding wickedneſſe, villanies, and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. O moſt mightie Lorde God Ieſus Chriſt, redéemer and ſauiour of the world, creator of heauen and earth, I do moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſéech thée, that it maye pleaſe thée no longer to ſuffer this wretche to worke far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſolations: Farther, that thou wilte graunte vnto me an vnworthye ſinner ſuche fauour, courage and valiancie, as by thy moſte pretious handes I maye accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe this thing, in ſuch wiſe, as none of thoſe that doe belong to him, whom, (with thy helpe, Lorde God, Ieſus Chriſte redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and ſauiour of the worlde, creator of heauen and earth) I purpoſe to ouercome, may haue any power againſt me. Howbeit in as much as thou arte the Supreme Lord God Ieſus Chriſte, redéemer and ſauiour of the world, creator of heauen and earth, if it pleaſe thee, that I leaue this miſerable life, I am well content, that it be ſo, and euer Lorde God, thy will be done. Thus moſt
<pb facs="tcp:1999:15"/>
mightie Lord God, Ieſus Chriſt, I beſéech thée with my whole hart, for the loue of thy moſt pretious paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it may pleaſe thée to graunte me conſtancie and patience, that I moſt miſerable ſinner may beare and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure whatſoeuer kinde of tormentes maye be laide vpon me, wherevnto I wil haue, as I ought, a moſt humble heart: if ſo it ſéeme good vnto thée O moſt mighty redéemer and ſauiour of the world, creator of heauen and earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="original">
               <p>
                  <hi>AVos Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo Redemptor y Saluador del mundo, Criador del Cielo y de la tierra, os offrezco ſiendo os ſeruido librar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me con vida, despues de hauer effectuado mi deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeo, vn velo muy rico: y a vos Nuestra Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora de Regona vna corona, vna ropa, vna lampara: y a vos Nuestra Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora de Arenzaſu vna corona: y a vos Nuestra Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora de Guadalupe vna Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona: a vos Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nueſtra Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora de Monſerrate: al ſancto Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixo de Burgos, nueſtra Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora del pilar de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoça.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="translation">
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:15"/>TO thée Lorde God, Ieſus Chriſt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer and Sauiour of the worlde, creator of heauen and earth, if it pleaſe thee to deliuer mée with life, I doe promiſe (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the finiſhing of my pretence,) a verye rich vaile: Alſo to thee our Lady of <hi>Regona,</hi> a crowne, a gowne, and a Lampe: To thée our Lady of <hi>Arancazu</hi> one crown: &amp; to thée our Lady of <hi>Guadalupe,</hi> one crowne: and to thée our Lord God Ieſus Chriſte. Alſo to our Lady of <hi>Montferrat:</hi> to the holy Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe of <hi>Burges:</hi> to our Lady of the Piller of <hi>Saragoſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="original">
               <p>
                  <hi>AVos Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Dios Ieſu Christo Redemptor y Saluador del mundo, os offrezco ſiendo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uido librarme con vida d'eſte effecto qua traygo entre manos vna ropa muy rica: y a vos Nuestra Senora de Vegonbaan vna corona: y vna ropa, y vna lampara: y a vos Nuestra Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora de Aranzacu vna corona: y a vos Nueſtra Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nora de Guadalupe vna corona: y a vos Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Dios Ieſu Christo del Crucifixo de Burgos cabal offrezco vna rica ropa, y offrezco yr en Roma a vna ſemana continuando.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="translation">
               <pb facs="tcp:1999:16"/>
               <head>The Copy of that which was written in the ſixth &amp; ſeuenth pages of <hi>Iohn Iaureguyes</hi> writing Tables.</head>
               <p>TO the Lorde God Ieſus Chriſte, redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and ſauiour of the world, I do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, if it pleaſe thée to deliuer me with life out of this enterpriſe whiche I haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hand, one very rich gowne: To thée our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Vegondaan</hi> one crown, one gowne, and one lampe: to thée our Lady of <hi>Arancazu</hi> one crowne: and to thée our Lady of <hi>Guada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lupa</hi> one crowne: and to thée Lord God Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte of the Crucifixe of <hi>Burges,</hi> I doe vowe one gowne richly furniſhed: and doe farther vowe to goe to <hi>Rome</hi> within one wéeke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="original">
               <p>
                  <hi>AL Angel ſan Gabriel me encomiendo con todo mi ſpiritu y coracon, paraque agora y ſie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre me ſea mi interceſſor a nueſtro Sen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>or Ieſu Christo, y a ſu hijo precioſiſſimo, y a la Virgen ſancta Maria, y a todos los Sanctos y Sanctas de la corte del cielo de guardarme y encaminarme y tenerme de ſu be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dita mano ſin que yo ſea muerto
<pb facs="tcp:1999:16"/>
ſubitamente, y me de gracia paraque pueda con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeguyr el buen zelo que tengo de ſalir con aquel effecto. Yen memoria deſto prometo de ayunar to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da vna ſemana entera (despues de ver me libre deſto) a pan y agua, y de rezar, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="translation">
               <head>In the tenth Page.</head>
               <p>I Do with my whole minde and hearte, commende me to the Aungell Sainct <hi>Gabriel,</hi> to the ende, that nowe and euer he may be my mediatour to our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt and to his moſt pretious ſonne, and to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and to all he Saincts and ſhe Saincts of the heauenly Court, that he will kéepe and conduct me, and with his bleſſed hand vphold me from ſodaine death, and to graunt me grace to attaine to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of my good zeale. In remembraunce whereof I doe promiſe, that if I eſcape frée from this déede, I will for one whole wéek faſt breade and water, and pray.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="original">
               <p>
                  <hi>DE ayunar todos los Viernes a interceſſion de la paſſion de nuestro Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor Ieſu Christo, y todos los Sabados a inuocation de nue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra
<pb facs="tcp:1999:17"/>
Senora la Virgen Maria, paraque yo ſea guardado deste tranſito, y me encamine a dar fin a este effecto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="translation">
               <head>In the fourteenth Page.</head>
               <p>TO faſt euerie Fryday in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration of the paſſion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and euerie Saturday for the inuocation of our Ladie the virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> to the ende I may be preſerued from this perill, and that ſhe may guide me to the ende of this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="original">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Hecho en la carcel deſta vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la de Anueres à <date>veinte de Marco, del an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1582.</date> En preſentia del S. Malgraue, Godefrido Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tens, Iacomo zuerio, y Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douico Blomarte Eſclauines d'ella.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ntonio de venero preſo, hijode Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Espan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ol naſcido de Bilbao en Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caia, de edad de dies y nueue à ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte annos teniendo los libros de Gasper d' Annastro, mercade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eſpanol, dize auer morado con e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:17"/>
dicho Anaſtro mas de dos annos.</p>
               <p>Preguntado s' y no ſaue quien ha eſcrito vn pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel o bilete muestrado à el declarante hallado ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre el muerto, el qual el domingo paſſado ha tirado con vn pistolete la perſona de ſu Excellentia, el Principe d' Orange, commençando el dicho bille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: Nuestro Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor Ieſu Christo, &amp;c. Dize ſer eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crito por mano de Iuan de Iaureguy.</p>
               <p>Preguntado quien es el dicho Iua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Iaureguy? Dize ſer Espan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ol de Bilbao en Biſcaya, ſobrino de Pedro d' Oroſco, mercader Espa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nol en Brujas, el qual Iuan vino morar con el dicho Anastro cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca el mez de Iulio paſſado, auiendo mie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres eſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y copiado las cartas del dicho Anastro y lo que le mando.</p>
               <p>Siendo al declarante muestrado el muerto y preg', ſi aquel es Iuan de Iaureguy ſobredicho? Dize que ſi, y que el auiendo el dicho Domingo oydo la miſſa ſalio de caſa cerca las onze horas an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes de comer, y auia entrado y ſalido la caſa tres o quatro vezes.</p>
               <p>Preguntado quien auia dictado al dicho Iuan el dicho billette? Dize que eſta cierto que ſe lo deue de auer dictado el dicho Anastro, por que el no tenia Iuyzio para hazerlo de ſi.</p>
               <p>Seyendo preguntado ſi no conoſcia el pistolete,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:18"/>
que le fué mostrado, con el qual es herido ſu Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentia por el dicho Iaureguy? Dize auer visto el miſmo pistolete o ſemejante à el, paſſado ſeis mezes en caſa del dicho Anastro, y que dicho A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastro ha embiado otros tres como ellos en Espa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, el vno à Don Fernando de Arieta, y el otro à Don Diego d' Alua, y el tercero a Pedro Lopes d' Arieta, ſin que ſabe quien los pueda auer fecho, quanto costaron, o quien les pago, ſea el dicho A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastro o ſu caxero.</p>
               <p>Preguntado donde vienne, y quien ha hecho la vela de çera verde en que esta abaxo imprimido el ſenal de la crux, que el dicho Iaureguy tenis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre ſu cuerpo nudo con vna medailla del Saluador y la Imagen de Nuestra Sennora Maria todo muestrado à el declarante? Dize que es vna de las velas que ſe da à algun paſſagero viſitando el Monasterio en Burgos en Espana, adonde esta el Crucifixo, y la Imagen esta hecha de los Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes en Madrid: pero no ſaue como el dicho Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy ha cobrado lo ſobredicho.</p>
               <p>Preguntado que fueron las postreras palabras que el dicho Iuan ha tenido co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> el declarante? Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ze que la postrera vez que le hablo dixo que e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaua muy bien determinado para executar y ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complir ſu empreſa, pues que ſe auia confeſſado, y
<pb facs="tcp:1999:18"/>
que por eſſo ſeria bueno que el declarante te ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſſe, ſobre que el declarante le respondio que no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſauia adonde yr, o ſaluar ſe: por estar cargado de los libros y papeles del dicho Anastro ſu amo, y que por eſſo quedaria cereo dellos como le auia prometido.</p>
               <p>Preguntado à quien el dicho Iaureguy ſe auia confeſſado? Dize à cierto frayle llamado Padre Antonio.</p>
               <p>Preguutado ſi el dicho Padre Antonio non ha ſauido d'estu empreſa, quando, y porquien? Dize que el declarante no ha comunicado dello con el padre Antonio, ny ha ouydo que ninguno en publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, ny ſecreto aya comunicado con el ſaluo que el dicho Iuan de Iaureguy le dixò que ſe auia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſado con el dicho Padre Antonio, y tratado d'eſto negocio, y que eran en el Anastro, Iaureguy, y el declarante, y que le auia abſuelto dello.</p>
               <p>Preguntado ſi no ſaue ſi el dico Gaspar de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro o otro vuieſſe ſemejante empreſa ſobre la perſona de la Sereniſſ. Reyna de Inglaterra, o ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre la del Sereniſſ. Ducque de Anjou? Dize que pienſa que non.</p>
               <p>Preguntado ſi conoſce la carta eſcrita en Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quercque à <hi>xvj.</hi> de Março, donde la ſobreſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on y tenor le fue preleydo? Dize que ſi, y ſer eſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta por las proprias manos del dicho Anastro: y ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bien
<pb facs="tcp:1999:19"/>
la otra carta ſerrada en ella es ſuya, y por el eſcrita.</p>
               <p>Preguntado ſi la carta eſcrita en Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelingues à xvij. d'eſte mez de Março eſtat tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bien eſcrita por el dicho Gaspar Anastro? Dize que ſi, y todo eſſo para que ſe effectuaſſe eſta em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſa como pareſce por el contenido d'ellas.</p>
               <p>Preguntado ſi el dicho Iaureguy no tenia algun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauallo presto, o otro remedio para ſaluar ſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpues de auer cometido el delito? Dize, que no: pero que estaua determinado de morir auiendo hecho el dicho efeto, y que era tan induzido del dicho Annastro para hazer dicho efeto, que paresçia, que era encantando, y que yua muy alegremente, para hazerlo fuera la caza del dicho Anastro, despues que auia oydo la miſſa, y auiendo almor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zando bibido vn golpe de Bastardo.</p>
               <p>Preguntado quien era el hombre à cauallo teni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo de diestro otto cauallo enſilado paſeando ſe al tiempo del dicho efetto delante la corte de ſu Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. Dize dello no ſaber nada, y que libramente declarara lo que dello ſupiera, pues que tiene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarado lo que mas importa, y ſennaladame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te no ſabe d'ello coſa alguna.</p>
               <p>Seyendo propuesto al dicho declarante que o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieſe de nombrar y mostrar todos los que cono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcia,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:19"/>
o ſabia que podrian auer ſabido de la dicha empreſa. Dize que perſona del mundo, ny de den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro ny de fuera d'esta villa ſabe hablar de la di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha empreſſa, mas que dicho declarante, y el dicho Iaureguy y Gaspar d' Annastro y Iuan de Yſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, y ſu hijo Pedro de Yſunca.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="translation">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Done in the Priſon of this tovvne of Antwerpe <date>the 20. of March 1582.</date> in the preſence of my Lorde the Marcgraue, Godfrey Montens, Iames Zuerius and Lewes Blommart, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifes of the ſaid towne.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANthony de Venero</hi> priſoner, the ſonne of <hi>Iohn,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard</hi> born in <hi>Bilbao</hi> in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcay,</hi> of the age of ninetene or twenty yeres, kéeper of the booke of accompts of <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> a marchaunt and <hi>Spaniard</hi> borne, ſaith, that he hath dwelt with the ſayd <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro</hi> aboue two yeares.</p>
               <p>Being aſked whether he knew who writ a certaine paper or remembraunce which was there ſhewed to the ſayde <hi>Anthonie,</hi> which bill was founde about the dead bodie of him who the Sunday before had diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a dagge againſt the perſon of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> which bill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:20"/>
Our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c. He ſaith that <hi>I. Iaureguy</hi> writ it with his own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded what that <hi>Iohn Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> is? He ſaith he is a <hi>Spaniard</hi> of <hi>Bilbao</hi> in <hi>Biſcay,</hi> the cooſin of <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Oroſco</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt &amp; <hi>Spaniard</hi> borne, remaining at <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> which <hi>Iohn</hi> came about the moneth of Iuly laſt paſt, to dwel w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> where hitherto he hath bin emploied in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying the letters of the ſayd <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> and in whatſoeuer elſe he commaunded him.</p>
               <p>The dead corps being ſhewed to the ſayd deponent, and he aſked whether it were the aforeſayd <hi>Iohn Iaureguy?</hi> He ſayth yea, and that the ſayd <hi>Iohn</hi> hauing the Sunday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heard Maſſe, departed out of the houſe about eleuen of the clocke before noone, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had thrée or foure times gone out and in at the ſaid houſe.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded who penned the ſaide bill for the ſayd <hi>Iohn:</hi> he ſayth that the ſaide bill ſhould ſurely be, of the penning of the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> bicauſe the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> was not of vnderſtanding ſufficient to haue done it.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether he knew not the dagge which was ſhewed him, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:1999:20"/>
the ſayd <hi>Iaureguy</hi> wounded his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie: He ſayth that he hath ſéene the ſame dagge or the like of it aboue ſixe monethes ſince in the houſe of the ſayd <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> who ſent thrée others like the ſame into <hi>Spaine.</hi> One to <hi>Don Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Arieta,</hi> an other to <hi>Don Diego</hi> of <hi>Alua</hi> and the third to <hi>Peter Lopes</hi> of <hi>Arieta:</hi> but he knoweth not who made them, how much they coſt, either who payed for them, whether the ſayd <hi>Annaſtro</hi> or his purſebearer.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, from whence came or who made the gréene waxe candel, vpon the nether ende whereof the ſigne of the Croſſe was painted, which the ſayd <hi>Iaureguy</hi> bare vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his naked bodie together with a quoine of the Sauiour, and the image of our Ladie <hi>Marie,</hi> all which was ſhewed to the ſayd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, he ſaith that it is one of the candels which vſually are giuen to pilgrimes when they viſite the monaſterie where the cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe of <hi>Burgos</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> doth ſtand: and that the Ieſuites made the image at <hi>Madrill</hi> but of whom the ſayd <hi>Iaureguy</hi> had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded what were the laſt
<pb facs="tcp:1999:21"/>
words that the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> vſed vnto the ſayd deponent: He ſayeth that the laſt time he ſpake with him he ſayde vnto him, that he was fully determined to execute and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his enterpriſe, conſidering he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie ſhriuen, wherefore it were good that the ſayd deponent ſaued him ſelfe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the ſayde deponent aunſwered, that he wiſt not whether to goe or where to ſaue him ſelfe, for that he ſtoode charged with his ſayd maſter <hi>Annaſtros</hi> books and writings, and therefore that according to his promiſe he woulde remaine with them.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded to whom the ſayde <hi>Iaureguy</hi> was ſhriuen, he ſaith to a certaine Monke named father <hi>Antony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether the ſayd fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Anthony</hi> knew of their enterpriſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or by whom: he ſaith that he this deponent neuer conferred with the ſayd father <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> neither knew that any other conferred with him either ſecretely nor openly, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that the ſayde <hi>Iohn Iaureguy</hi> tolde him that he had confeſſed him ſelfe to the ſayd fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Anthony,</hi> &amp; had conferred with him of this matter, whereunto <hi>Annaſtro, Iaureguy</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:21"/>
and he ſhe deponent were priuy, and that he had abſolued him.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether he knewe, whether the ſayd <hi>Iaſper Annaſtro</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had framed the like practiſe againſt the perſon of the moſt noble Quéene of <hi>England,</hi> or againſt the moſt noble Duke of <hi>Anjou?</hi> ſayth that he thinketh no.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether he knew the letter written fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Dunkirke</hi> the <hi>16.</hi> of March the ſuperſcription and tenure whereof were red vnto him, ſayth, yea, and that <hi>Annaſtro</hi> wrote it with his owne hand. Alſo that the other letter incloſed therein, is of the ſame ſort, and likewiſe written by him.</p>
               <p>Being dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded whether the letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from <hi>Graueling</hi> the <hi>17.</hi> of this moneth of March were wrote by the ſayd <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> he ſayth yea, and that all was done for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to the execution of this enterpriſe, as is euident by the contentes of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded whether the ſaid <hi>Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> had any houſe readye, or any other meane to ſaue him ſelfe after the execution of this treſpaſſe, he ſayth, no: but that he was fully reſolued to die after he had broght
<pb facs="tcp:1999:22"/>
this offence to paſſe: for the ſayd <hi>Annaſtro</hi> had ſo perſwaded him to doe this déede, that he ſéemed euen bewitched: in ſuche wiſe as after he had hearde maſſe, and broken his faſt, hauing drunke a good cuppe of Baſtard he departed very chéerefully out of the houſe of the ſayd <hi>Annaſtro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being demaunded what he was who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on horſeback &amp; leading a ſpare horſe ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led walked vp and downe before his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies Court at the ſame time that this déede was done: he ſayth, that he knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereof: alſo that fréely he would ſhew whatſoeuer he knewe, conſidering that he hath alreadie declared vnto them matters of greater importance: and that hereof e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially he is ignorant.</p>
               <p>The ſayd <hi>Venero</hi> being willed to name and reueale all thoſe whome he knewe or thought to be priuie to any thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſayde enterpriſe: he ſayeth that neither one nor other, neither in the towne nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where, are able to ſpeake any thing of his enterpriſe, but him ſelfe, this deponent, <hi>Iaureguy, Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro, Iohn</hi> of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ca,</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Hunca.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <div type="deposition_original">
               <pb facs="tcp:1999:22"/>
               <head>La Depoſition de Antonio Venero: la quelle de ſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre mouuement il a faicte, &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntairement eſcript &amp; ſouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignée de ſa propre main.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>O Antonio de Venero, vezino de Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bao, hijo de Iuan de Venero, de edad de diez y nueue a veynte annos poco mas o menos, aſſistente en la caſay negocios del Gaspar de Annastro vezino de Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria, deſde veynte dias del mes de Enero del anno de <hi>1580.</hi> hasta treze de Março de <hi>1582.</hi> declaro lo ſeguiente que me ha acconteſcido con el dicho Gaspar de Annastro, ſiendo pregunt ado dello del ſenor Mulgraue, Burgomaestre, y Eſclaunineo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta villa de Anberes, diziendo la verdad ſobre iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramenta, y ſobre mi alma y mi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcientia, promet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienno dezir toda la verdad ſin encubrir coſa al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guna, por auerme prometiendo los dichos ſennores Malgraue, Burgomaestre, y Eſclauines a inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion del ſennior Esteuan Roquen Coronel de la dicha villa de Anberes, de diziendo todo lo que me consta, de darme muerte honroſa, y a medita
<pb facs="tcp:1999:23"/>
de mi deſſeo y contentamiento, y Saſerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te para confeſſarme y comulgarme por lo que roca à la honra de mi linnage. E yo el dic ho Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio de Venero confiando en la palabra y nobleza de los dichos ſennores de que aſſi lo cumpliran, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go lo ſeguiente.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRIMERAMENTE,</hi> es, que Iuan do Yſunca vezino de victoria, proueedor de fue de las arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das en estos estados, eſcriuio al dicho Annastro vna carta de Liſbona, aura diez meſes poco mas menos, en que le pedia diuerſos menages, ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erle eſcripto hastae entonces, diziendole que ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia por coſa nueua el auer carta ſuya, mas que lo hazia por estar en Liſbona, ſupplicandole le em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biaſe lo que pedia. Y el dicho Gasper de Annaſtro le respondiò con palabras corteſanas, eſcuſando ſe de no embiar ſelos, auiendolo hecho por no auerle embiado dineros, y por verſe a la ſazon rico, y ſin gana de fiarle lo que le pedia. Y el dicho Iuan de Yſunca respondio à estio, rogandole ſe los embi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſe, porque le hazian mucha falta, hallandoſe en Liſbona por conſeruar ſu autoridad, atento que entendia que ſu Magestad le queria dar vn car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go muy honroſo, y que lo hizieſſe, porque le co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> carta vn negocio de gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſſima importancia, y que redondaria en gran bien, honor, y beneficio ſuyo. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra
<pb facs="tcp:1999:23"/>
vez le respondiò con nueuas eſcuſas, y d'eſtilo corteſano, y en effecto jamas le embio dichos me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>najes: pero le eſcriuio que que negocio podia ſer el que lo cometia, y de tanta importancia, y que ſe lo auiſaſſe. Eſtas des cartas arriba vi yo el dicho An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio de Venero, y despues vino la respuesta d'eſta carta, en que el dicho Iuan de Yſunça declaro el negocio, y leyo la carta: y de entonces aca me or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denò a mi el dicho Antonio de Venero que no le a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brieſſe ninguna carta que vtnieſſe cerrada à la corte ſaena. Y en eſte tiempo, que pudieron ſer cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co o ſeys meſes, poco mas o menos, anduuieron los dichos Iuan de Yſunça y Gaspar de Annastro en demandas y reſpuestas, eſcriutendoſe cartas vnos a otros con mucho ſecreto, y el dicho Gaspar de Annastro le respondia en ſu camara ſiempre de ſu mano, cerrando las cartas con lacre, y lo mas disfraçado que podia. En todo eſte tiempo estuue yo el dicho Antonio de Venero innocente de tal caſo, echando imaginacion que le trataua caſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miento con la hija de Iuan Ruyz de Vergara, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano de Franciſco Ruyz de Vergara, que ha vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uido en Anberes, por auerſelo eſcripto al dicho Gaspar de Annastro donna Maria de Yſunça ſu madre, y que como ſabian eſtaua rico, y era de los masqualificados de dicha Vitoria, ſe ladarian
<pb facs="tcp:1999:24"/>
con muchos ducados. Y como digo yo el dicho An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio de Venero entendi que estos ſerian los ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos y que tardaeuan en reſoluerſe, porque pediria el dicho Annaſtro aun mas dote de lo que of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſcian, por gozar con mas largueſa deſu graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad. Despues parece ſer que ſe perdieron dos naos Flamencas que yuan a Laredo, y que fue robada en Plemua la nao de Philipe Dorio que yua tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bien à Biſcaya. En las quales dichas tres naos tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo muy grueſſas perdidas, de que el ſe vio con gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo trabajo y deſcontento de espiritu, ſin ſaber que hazerſe para poder paſſar adelante con ſu honor. En este instante eſciruio el dicho Iuan de Yſunça al dicho Gaspar de An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aſtro, ſin ſaberlo yo tampoco, yera que hizieſſe matar a ſu Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia el Principe d'Orange, y que lo tenta trata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu Magestad en grandiſſimo ſecreto, ſin que nadie lo ſupieſſe, ſino entre los dos: y auia hecho ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer à ſu Magestad vna capitulacion firmado de ſu mano, en que leprometia, despues de ſabido la nueua ciertà dela muerte de ſu Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, ochen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ta mil duchados en dinero, o el valor d'ellos en renta, y vn habito de Sanctiago, y que esto esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua por eſcrito, y que aun haria otras muchas coſas, de darle cargos honroſos: porque auia dicho y aſſegurado el dicho Iuan de Yſunça à ſu
<pb facs="tcp:1999:24"/>
Magestad, que el dicho Annastr era vn hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre de muy claero entendimiento, y de muchas pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das. En este instante ami el dicho Antonio de Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero no me consta que este negocio lo ſupieſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona naſcida: antes me aſſeguro al parecer mio, que por ningunae coſa del mundo ſe deſcubriera el dicho Gaspar de Annastro de n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nguna nacion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrangera para tal caſo. Y puesto caſo que en An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beres no ay Espan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oles à quien poderlo deſcubrir, torno à dezir, que verdaderame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te me paerece que no lo dixo à perſona ninguna, y esto affirmo aſſi por poder penetrar de otra ceſa. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſte tiempo, aura como vn mes, tuuo recelos de otra deſgracia nueuamente, de que deuian de ester attaiados de hazie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do de mercaderes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quien el tenta muy gru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſointereſſe, de qui antidad de nueue mil quinient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as libras de grueſſo, poco mas o menos de mercade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias qu' el le au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ado, y cangazones<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> auiae hecho para embiar à ellos, por cuenta de algunos, Ingleſes de Londres, y par letras de ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bio que auiae acceptado y pagaedo llanamente por ellos. Y viendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tos trabaios, y que d'eſte vltimo el no tenia culpa alguna, pues ſi a el le hazias hancoroto con tanta ſumma, el no lo podia remediar en ningunà manera, de ſe auſentar tambien. Y en este inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te me llamó à ſu camara a mi el dicho Antonio
<pb facs="tcp:1999:25"/>
de Venero, y encargandome mucho el ſecreto, y llorando muchas lagrimas, me dixo la ſubstancia declarada, y de lo tratado con el dicho Iuan de Y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunca, y me mostro algunas cartas de las qu'l dicho Iuan de Yſunça le auia eſcripto, en que le hazia buenas todas las promeſſas ſuſo decluradas, y las cartas venian eſcriptas diebolica e ingenio ſame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſin firma, y el dicho Iuan de Yſunça pareſce ſer que dio cuenta del negocio en Espa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na a vn hijo ſuyo que estaua en Madrid, llamado Pedro de Y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunça Le Queytio, y este miſmo tambien le eſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia por muy buen termino, aſſegurandole la miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſubstancia con muchas prendas, y firmandoſe en la firma <hi>Apodaca.</hi> Estas cartas quemo en el apoſento despues de auerme moſtrado (como digo) la ſubstancia d'ellas. <hi>Y</hi> en esto comenſo à diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rir con migo, dizendo, que no queria verſe à reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir tantas affrentas, como ſe le aparetauan, y que ſe queria encomendar à Dios de todo coraçon, y matar el miſmo à ſu Excellencia el Principe de Ora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: y que ſi le acauaſſen, por cierto que el que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria quador alli, por que era meior morir, que no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uir (ſiendo el quien era) en affrenta, de que le di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xieſſen por el en la bolſa de Anberes, mirad aquel hombre que a hecho bancaroto, y que llegandolas coſas a este termino ninguno, conſideraria à que
<pb facs="tcp:1999:25"/>
no era la culpa ſuya: ſino echarle mucha culpa quando no la tuuieſſe, y que deuia muchos dineros en Anberes a los principales, y que tenian mando en la tierra, y le perſeguirian cruelmente, y que aſſi determinaua de morir, y que y a ſabia que lleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua la muerte tragada: pero que conesto ſe enca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briria, y queno ſe attribuyria a dar nombre de ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caroto à ſu deſgracia. Todo lo dezia llorando. E yo viendole tan de ſconſolado, lloraua mucho mas, y le roguè, que por amor de Dios no buſcaſſe con ſus manos la muerte, y que tuuieſſe patiencia de las coſas que Dios hazia, y que pues no era ſuya la culpa, reſistieſſe al trabaio que le ſobreuenia, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrando rostro à ſus acrecdores, y la razon en la mano, que le destruyan Pedro Nunnez de Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulu, y Pedro de çubiaur, y que con esto ſe ſuffri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſie. El me respondia, que no ternia rostro para mirar à nadie, y que aſſi estaua en ſu propoſito, e yo ſe lo contradezia mucho, diziendo otra vez, que lo encomendaſſe todo à Dios y aguardaſſe à la deſgracia. En estas platicas (que eran vndia de labor à la tarde, despues de la bolſa) entro en ſu apoſento Andres de la Maça que viue en caſa, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocente de todo, y aſſi ſe quedo esto aſſi ſin hoblar mas d'ello a quello noche por reſpecto della venida del dicho Andres de la Maça. Otro dia à la man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nana (estando en ſu camara) me embiò à llamar,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:26"/>
y dixo, Pues como os va, Antonio hermano? y le respondi, que con mucha tristeza: y me comencò tratar otar vez de lo paſſado, y que ſi el no mata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua à ſu Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cia, no ſabia à quien encome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dar ſe, ſi yo no fueſſe prouar laventura con Iua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy, vezmo de Bilbao, cryado ſuyo, que ayudaua à eſcriuir en el co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tador, porque le pareſcia moç<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminado para qualqui era coſa, y pobre, E yo el dicho Antonio de Venero le reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di, que ſeria gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo cargo de conſciencia, que el dicho Anaſtro dieſſe occaſion que murieſſe el dicho Iuan de Iau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reguy mala muerte, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rque (como querian tanto à ſu Excellencia en toda la tierra.) quando lo aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſe de hazer, le harian pieças. El dezia, que no, ſino prenderle, y ſaber del à que fin lo auia hecho, y que en esto ſe paſſarian ocho dias, despues que el vuieſſe hecho el effecto, y que para esto podia pàr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir el dicho Annastro de Anberes quatro dias antes que el lo hizieſſe, y yria à Cales, y de alla de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpacharia vn correo à Rauayn, que es Pedro de Yſunça, Le queytio, hijo de Iuan de Yſunça, en que auiſaſſe à ſu Magestad, que auia ſalido para tal effecto, y que quedaua concertado, y que de Cales yria al ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po del principe de Parma. Y qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe la nueua de la muerte, embiaria aca deſde el ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po vna Tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peta, pidie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſaluaſſen al dicho Iuan de Iau. la vida, y que el meſmo Gaſpar de Anaſtro
<pb facs="tcp:1999:26"/>
e ſcreuiria ſobre el negoci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, declarandoſe à algu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos amigos de la Villa pidiando la vida del dicho, y embia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do firmas en blanco del Principe de Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, paraque estos ſennores padieſſen lo que quiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſen en ſu vo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taeja de la religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-frera, y todo lo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, y que con eſte auria paz deſpues de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> el Principe de Orange. En esto entro à lacramara vn muchacho Flamenco del dicho Gaſpar de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastro, que le lleuo conſigo, llamado Iuanico, y le dixo, que llamaſſe à Iuan de Iaureguy el qual eſt aua eſcriuiendo èn el contador y vino, y qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tró, me dixo à mi que me ſalieſſe del apoſento, y quedo con el en el apoſento platicando. Y de alli vn rato me llamò à mi, y dixo que Iaureguy queria hazer aquello por amor d'el, y porſu honra, y que le auia mostrado vn pun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al con que lo auia de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, estando en la tabla, o en conuerſaecion, y me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terle elpun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al por detras de la oreja, y paſſarle, y que e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iaureguy lo queria hazer de buena gana: à mi me dexo que que me pareſcia, y le respondi, que miraſſe por lo que tecaua a la conſciencia, y que ſi tal fueſſe, padeceria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much as muertes los Eſpanno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les que estaua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> en Anberes, de peſar de ver muer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, al Principe ſi le mataſſen, y que yo me queriayr de la tierra por no peligrar de la vida: y me dixo, que nó tuuieſſe miedo, que como el Iaureguy dixiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe la verdad claramente, no tocaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> en la caſa, ni
<pb facs="tcp:1999:27"/>
haria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coſa ninguna. En esto aconſejo ad Iaureguy que por amor de ſu ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ra y d'el, que quedaſſe reſuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to el hecho, y que aquel miſmo dia fueſſe à espiar como comia ſu Excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cia, y aſſi lo hizo tres o qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro vezes: y de zia, que tenia gran eſpera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ça de ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerlo, y aqui tenia gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des platicas co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> el Iaureguy, como perſona que auia de acometer tal coſa. Y pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſando mas en ello, à la poſtre estuuiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> en duda, de ſi ſeria con pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nal, o pistolete. Y el Iaureguy dezia que nunca auia tir ado pistolete, ni ſabia como ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarlc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y le dixo, que lo fueſſe à prouar en alguna parte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> algun amigo, dizie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do que el dicho Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy fueſſe Flamenco, y que no ha blaſſe otra le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gua: y le dixo, de ſi, como lo hizo, Anda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do en esto, llego cartade Londres, en que dezia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, que Pedro de çu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biaur era auſentado, y con esta occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> le to mo gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gana de yrſe, y ſe de ſpedio en la bolſa de algunos, y ſe fue arrebatadame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. El Martes, ò Miercoles deſpediendoſe de todos los de caſa innocente men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te para boluer luego (ſaluo del dicho Iuan Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy, y de mi el dicho Antonio de Venero) y me eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criuio deſde Bruias dos cartas, la vna general, y la otra d'eſte negocio: de que la general mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre à Mortin de Varron, Pedro de la Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio Spinola, y à algunos otros, y despues la que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, y di la otra carta al dicho Iaureguy, y la leyó,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:27"/>
por<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dezia le pareſcia fueſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pistolete, y el otro dixo que eſtaua bien, y que aſſi lo haria y lo dezia con mocha alegria, y quemo tambien la otra car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, y me dixo, que ſe queria co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſar, y ſe ſue fuera de caſa à hazarlo, ſin que yo preguntaſſe al dicho Iaureguy con quien, y me dixo ſe auia confeſſado y comulgado, y despues estaua ya presto para ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarlo quando el qui ſieſſe, ſin aguardar à nada. Y aſſi este Domingo paſſado, diez y ocho d'este oyo Miſſa en caſa como à las onze horas, y despues ſe fue, e hizo lo que parece ſer, que cierto aun yo lo no ſe. Y para de ſcargo de mi conſcientia digo que no me consta que tenga ninguno otro culpa en este negocio: y que aſſilos que mas estan preſos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſer ſueltos y libres, por hallar los yo innocentes. Y ſi à mi el dicho Antonio de Venero (por auer deſcubierto mi coracon, y dicho quanto he podido y ſe me ha accordado) quiſieren V. S. hazer mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia de ſaluarle la vida (pues el que hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo el mal es muerto, e yo no fuy auctor d'ello) lo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conoſcere toda mi vida.</p>
               <p>El dicho Gaspar de Annastro nos prometio al dicho Iuan de Iaureguy, y à mi el dicho Antonio de Venero, que ſi a quello ſe hazia, nos ternia por proprios hijos, y que no auria coſa partida, ſino que ſu hazienda ſeria nuestra propria: y otras pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras
<pb facs="tcp:1999:28"/>
desta manera. Y el dicho Iaureguy dixò, que no queria ninguna coſa, y que lo hazia por amor d'el, y por auer comida ſu pan, e yo le quité el ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brero temblando, y dandole á entender como te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia de la muerte, y el me aſſeguraua que no me tocarian en vn pelo de la cabeca.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Soubſignê. Godofridus Montens. Zuerius. Blomart. Antonio de Venero.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Siendo eſta confeſsion preleyda al dicho declarante fuera de la carcel debaxo del cie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ha perſiſtidio en ella, liendo aſsi verdad en preſentia de los Eſclauines aqui abaxo firmado fecho à xxvj. de Marco. 1582.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Zuerius. Blomart.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition_translation">
               <pb facs="tcp:1999:28"/>
               <head>The depoſition of <hi>Anthonie Venero,</hi> which of his owne motion he made and willinglie writ and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with his owne hande.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Anthonie</hi> of <hi>Venero,</hi> borne in <hi>Bilbao,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> of the age of <hi>19.</hi> or <hi>20.</hi> yeares little more or leſſe, aſſiſtant in the houſe &amp; affaires of <hi>Iaſpar</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro</hi> borne in <hi>Victoria,</hi> from the <hi>20.</hi> daye of Ianuarie, <hi>1580.</hi> vnto the xiij. of March <hi>1582.</hi> do as followeth declare, what hapned vnto me with the ſaid <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of examined by my Lordes the <hi>Marcgraue,</hi> Borowmaiſters and Shirifes of this towne of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and do promiſe vppon my oathe, ſoule and conſcience, to ſhew the whole truth thereof: not to cloke or conceale anye thing, whervpon the ſaide Lordes, the <hi>Marcgraue,</hi> Borowmaiſters and Shirifes, haue by the intreatie of the Lord <hi>Steuen Racquet Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> of the ſaide towne of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> promiſed me, that confeſſing whatſoeuer I do knowe, they wil grant me an honorable death, agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:1999:29"/>
to my deſire and contentation, with a Prieſte alſo to confeſſe me and to conferre withall, becauſe it concerneth the honour of my ſtock: I <hi>Anthonie</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> repoſing my ſelfe vpon the word and nobilitie of the ſaide Lords, touching the accompliſhment thereof, do ſay as followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt that <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunca</hi> borne in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> aforetime Commiſſioner euer the furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the armies in theſe partes, writte a letter to <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> of <hi>Liſbone,</hi> aboute ten monethes ſince, wherein he requeſted of him certaine goods, whereof he had neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore written vnto him: he ſaide it woulde be newes to him to ſée any of his letters, &amp; that he did this, that ſo he mighte be at <hi>Liſbone</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſting him to ſende him that which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. Hereunto the ſaide <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro</hi> aunſwerrd in friendlie wordes, excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe for not ſending them, as well vpon that he had not ſent money, as becauſe he founde not him ſelfe of wealth ſufficiente, and ſo could not truſt forth that which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. Whereto <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunca</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, requeſting him to ſende the ſaide moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables, for that at <hi>Liſbone</hi> he ſtoode in greate
<pb facs="tcp:1999:29"/>
néede of them for the conſeruation of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie, conſidering that his Maieſtie woulde committe vnto him a verie honorable office: and that therefore he woulde doe it: for hée woulde communicate vnto him a matter of verie great importance, which would redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to his great benefite &amp; honour. To the whiche the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro</hi> replied againe with newe excuſes and curteſies, but in déede ſente him not the ſaid moueables, only he deſired to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what matter of ſo great importance it might be that he would communicate vnto him, wherof he deſired him to aduertiſe hym. Theſe two letters aforeſaid did I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> ſée, afterward came the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of this letter wherin the ſaid <hi>I.</hi> of <hi>Y ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> opened the matter, &amp; when <hi>Annaſtro</hi> had red the ſaide letter, he commaunded me <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> aforeſaid from thenceforth not to open any letter comming ſealed after the maner of the Court: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that time, which might be about <hi>5.</hi> or <hi>6.</hi> monthes ſince, the ſaide <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunca</hi> and <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> haue proſecuted their purpoſes and anſweres, each writing to other verie ſecretlie, and the ſaide <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> ſtill anſwering his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:1999:30"/>
with his owne hande, in his chamber cloſing his letters with harde waxe the moſte cloſlieſt that might be. All this while was I <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> ignoraunt of this facte, imagining that it was ſome mariage mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the daughter of <hi>Iohn Ruiz</hi> of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gara</hi> the brother of <hi>Fraunces Ruiz</hi> of <hi>Verga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> who had dwelt in this towne of <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe,</hi> and the rather becauſe her mother the Ladie <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Yſunca</hi> hadde written to the ſayd <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> alſo that knowing him to be wealthie and of the beſt qualetied in <hi>Victoria</hi> they would beſtow her vpon him with ſome good number of Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kats. And as I ſay, <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed theſe to be the ſecretes, and geſſed that they deferred the finall reſolution, becauſe the ſayd <hi>Anaſtro</hi> required for her dowrie and to the maintenaunce of her porte, more than they did offer: It afterward (as I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber) fell ſo out, that two Flemiſh veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſayling towards <hi>Laredo</hi> wer drowned, alſo that at <hi>Plemue</hi> the barke of <hi>Philip Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> which was bound to <hi>Biſcay</hi> was robbed, in which thrée veſſels he loſt much, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he grewe into great care and anguiſh of
<pb facs="tcp:1999:30"/>
minde, as one ignorant how to behaue him ſelfe to ſaue his credit, at which inſtant the ſayd <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunca</hi> writ to the ſayd <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> vnwitting to me: the effect whereof was, that he ſhoulde procure the ſlaughter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: wherof he had delt with his Maieſtie ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſecretlie, in ſuche wiſe, as none but they two were acquainted therewith: alſo that he had procured his Maieſtie to ſet downe a certaine capitulation whiche alſo he had ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his owne hande, wherein his ſaide Maieſtie promiſed vpon the certaine news of his excellencies death, to giue to the ſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro 80000.</hi> Duckets in ſiluer or the value therof in lands, togither with a commander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>S. Iames.</hi> That this was ſet downe in writing, alſo that he woulde beſtow on him great benefittes with ſundrie honorable offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: for the ſaide <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunca</hi> had told and aſſured his Maieſtie that the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> was a man of verie good capacitie, and greats wealth. All this while, I <hi>Anthonie</hi> of <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> doe not thinke that anye one was able to ſpeake thereof, but rather in my opinion I durſt aſſure my ſelfe that in any wiſe the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:1999:31"/>
                  <hi>Annaſtro</hi> woulde not make any of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer nation or condition, priuie therevnto: ſo that as in <hi>Antwerpe</hi> there be no <hi>Spaniards</hi> able to detect him, ſo do I againe affirme, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely I thinke he diſcloſed it to none: which I doe the rather verifie, becauſe I can not other wiſe thinke. Now ſhortly after this, and as it were a moneth ſince he had ſome inckling of an other new miſchance, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of two Merchants, that were aboute to break, by whom he was in hazard of <hi>9500.</hi> 
                  <abbr>lb.</abbr> ſterling, or thereabout, for certaine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe that he hadde ſent them, and other goods vppon accompts of ſundrie Engliſhe men of <hi>London:</hi> as alſo by reaſon of certain billes of exchaunge whiche he had accepted and faithfully payed to their vſes: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſéeing him ſelfe entangled in ſo manye troubles, alſo, that of this laſt loſſe he was in no default, and not knowing any reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but by abſenting himſelfe, conſidering they had played bankerupte with ſo greate ſummes of his: he cauſed me <hi>Anthonie</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> to be called into his Chamber, and charging me verie ſore to be ſecreate, wyth teares running down his chéekes, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:1999:31"/>
vnto me the ſubſtance of the aforeſaide treatie with <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunça,</hi> ſhewing mee certaine of thoſe Letters, whiche the ſaide <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunça</hi> had writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he aſſured him of all the promiſes aboue ſpecified, which letters were written diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly and ſubtilly without any ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and it ſeemed, that the ſaide <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ça,</hi> hath imparted this matter to a ſonne of his, who remained at <hi>Madril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> called <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Yſunça le Queytio,</hi> who alſo writte to him in verye good ſpéeches, aſſuring him of the ſubſtance of al the premiſes diuerſly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming himſelfe in the ſubſcription <hi>Apodaca.</hi> Theſe Letters, hauing as I ſaide, ſhewed me the ſubſtaunce of them, did he burne in his Chamber: and therevppon entred into diſcourſe with me, ſaying, that he neither woulde ne could digeſt ſo manye ſhames as were prouided for him: therfore that commending himſelfe to almightie God wyth all his hearte, he would with his own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſlay my Lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his excellencie, &amp; that in caſe he were ſlaine about the execution therof, yet in trueth he had rather periſh in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place, as coueting ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:1999:32"/>
to die than to liue ſo diſhonorably, that it ſhoulde be ſaide of him in the Burſe at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> ſée, yonder man is become ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerupt: whiche, if it ſhoulde ſo fall out, no man woulde iudge where the faulte is, but would rather impute it vnto him, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe he were not faultie. Alſo, that he ought much money in <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> euen to the beſte, and to ſuche as there bare authoritie, who would with rigour procéede againſte hym, and therfore that he determined to die, yea, and that alreadie he had digeſted death, but that by this meanes he ſhould couer and get glorie to his bankeruptſhip and diſcredite. All this ſpake he with teares: wherevpon I ſéeing him ſo diſcomforted, wept much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and beſought him for Gods loue not to ſeke his death by his own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in Gods doings: &amp; ſéeing the fault was not in himſelfe, to withſtand ſuche aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as might happen in ſhewing a good face to his creditours, and to let them know the reaſons, how <hi>Peter Nunnes</hi> of <hi>Arbule,</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>çubiaur</hi> vndid him, and that hée ſhoulde repoſe himſelfe vpon this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he aunſwered, that he had not the face to
<pb facs="tcp:1999:32"/>
looke vpon any man, and therefore that hée was determined to perſiſte in his purpoſe: wherein I contraried him ſtiffely, ſundrye times willing him to refer al to God, &amp; to attend better hap. Vpon this communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which paſſed in an euening vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a working day after Burſe time) <hi>Andrew de la Maça,</hi> who notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding he remaineth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame houſe, is innocent of al, came into his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſo that by reaſon of the ſaide <hi>Andrewes</hi> comming in, we brake off talke for that night. The next morning the ſaide <hi>Anaſtro</hi> being in his chamber, ſent for me, and ſaid: Now, brother <hi>Anthony</hi> how doe you? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, but heauely: herevppon he began againe to reenter into the former matter, ſaying, that if he himſelfe ſhoulde not ſlaye his excellencie, he wiſt not to whom to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the doing thereof, excepte peraduenture to his man <hi>Iohn Iaureguy,</hi> borne in <hi>Bilbao,</hi> who holpe to write in the Counting houſe, becauſe he ſemed a ſtaied and reſolute yong man to any intent whatſoeuer, and poore withall. Then I <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that it woulde be a great burthen to his conſcience, if the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:1999:33"/>
procure the ſaide <hi>Iaureguy</hi> any vile death: for ſéeing his excellencie was ſo well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued throughout the whole towne, he coulde no ſooner haue done the déede, but he ſhould be hewen in péeces. Nay, ſaid <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> but they wil rather apprehend him, to the ende to learne for what purpoſe he did it, ſo as <hi>7.</hi> or <hi>8.</hi> dayes after the deed, would be ſpent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any execution, &amp; that therefore the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> mighte departe from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> four dayes before the déede, &amp; ſo go to <hi>Calais,</hi> from whence he might diſpatch a Poſte to <hi>Apodaca,</hi> who is <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Yſunça le Queytio,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn Yſunça,</hi> to the ende to giue his Maieſtie to vnderſtande, that he was departed from the purpoſe agréede vppon, then that from <hi>Calais</hi> he woulde goe to the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> his Campe, and thence ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing newes of the ſlaughter, he would ſend a trumpet to begge the life of the ſaide <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Iaureguy:</hi> Alſo, that <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> himſelfe would write concerning that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; open himſelf vnto ſundrie hys friends in the towne, requiring the life of the ſaid <hi>Iaureguy,</hi> and ſending blanckes ſigned by the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> to the ende theſe
<pb facs="tcp:1999:33"/>
Lords might aſke what they liſte for theyr own adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Religious <hi>Vreed</hi> and all other matters, alſo that there withal after the prince of <hi>Orenges</hi> death they ſhould enioy and aſſured peace. Herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Flemiſh boy belonging to the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro</hi> named <hi>Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nico,</hi> whom he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him, came into the Chamber, whom he commanded to call <hi>Iohn Iaureguy</hi> who was writing in the Counting houſe, when he was come he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me to depart out of the Chamber, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a while talked with him, he called me again, and ſhewed me that <hi>Iaureguy</hi> for his ſake and Honor would do it, alſo that he had ſhewed him a dagger wherewith he ſhoulde kil him either at the Table or in any other companie by thruſting in the Dagger and wounding him behinde the eare: that <hi>Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> would doe this with a verie good will, whervpon he aſked my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I anſwered that he ſhoulde looke well vnto it, becauſe it touched his conſcience: further, becauſe that if this matter were broughte to paſſe, they would ſlaie all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>Antwerpe</hi> for ſorrow of the Princes death, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had rather forſake the town tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture my life. But he willed me not to feare,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:34"/>
ſaying that although <hi>Iaureguy</hi> ſhould ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly confeſſe the truth, yet would no man medle with his houſe, neither wold ther be any fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther purſuite: and therfore he counſelled the ſaide <hi>Iaureguy</hi> in that matter to continue ſtedfaſt for the loue of his honour and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: alſo the ſame day to go to eſpie in what manner his excellencie did eate, whiche he did thrée or foure times, ſo that he ſaide he was in good hope to bring his purpoſe to paſſe. After this he vſed much ſpéech with the ſaid <hi>Iaureguy,</hi> as with the man who ſhould commit ſuch a hainous fact. Finally, hauing better conſidered of the matter, they began to doubte whether it were better to be done with a Dagger or with a Dagge: for <hi>Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> ſaid, that he neuer ſhot in Dagge, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knewe howe to diſcharge it, the other willed him to repaire to ſome friend of hys to trie it, and to counterfeite himſelfe to be a Fleming, and not to vſe anye other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, whereto he graunted, and did ſo. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe practiſes there came letters from <hi>London,</hi> importing, that <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>çubiaur</hi> had abſented himſelfe, vpon which occaſion he thought beſt to departe, ſo as hauing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched
<pb facs="tcp:1999:34"/>
ſome at the Burſe, ſodainely vppon a Tewſday or Wedneſday, hauing taken his leaue of all the houſholde, he wente his way, ſeming as if he would ſhortly come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, except to the ſayd <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Iaureguy</hi> &amp; me <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Venero,</hi> and from <hi>Bruges</hi> he writ me two Letters, the one generall, the other concerning this matter: The generall Letter I ſhewed to <hi>Martin</hi> of <hi>Varion, Peter de la Penna, Anthony Spinula,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and ſo burned it. The other I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to <hi>Iaureguy</hi> who read it, becauſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſaide that he thought the Dagge redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: the other ſaide that he could well doe it ſo, the which he ſpake verie chéerefully &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burned this letter alſo, and tolde me that he woulde be ſhriuen, and ſo went forth of the doores, neither did I euer aſke him to what Confeſſour he woulde goe. Afterwarde hée tolde me that he was ſhriuen and houſe led, and that now he was readie vpon anye op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie without any lette to execute hys purpoſe. Thus, vpon this laſt Sunday, the <hi>18.</hi> of this moneth, about eleuen of the clock he heard Maſſe in the houſe and ſo departed, and did that which ſéemeth to be done, not
<pb facs="tcp:1999:35"/>
that I doe certainely know it as yet: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the diſcharge of my conſcience I doe ſay, that I cannot perceiue any other to bée guiltie of this déede, and therefore that the others who are apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed and deliuered, becauſe in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they be innocent. Nowe therefore, if youre Lordſhips would graunt to me <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> pardon, &amp; to ſaue my life, as hauing opened the verie botome of my heart, and ſaide all that I knowe, beſides that, he who committed the miſchiefe, is dead already, I ſhould be bound to you all my life long.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the ſaide <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> promiſed vnto vs the ſaide <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy,</hi> and me <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Venero,</hi> that this being accompliſhed, he woulde accompte vs as his own naturall children: alſo, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be parted betwéene vs, but that all ſhoulde be our owne proper goodes, and ſuche like ſpéeches. The ſaide <hi>Iaureguy</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he woulde haue nothing, but that that which he did, he did for his loue, and becauſe he had eaten his breade: and I quaking, putte off my hatte, giuing him to vnderſtande how ſore I feared death, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb facs="tcp:1999:35"/>
he aſſured me that no man wold once touch any haire of my head.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>This confeſsion being red vnto the ſaide deponente without the priſon vppon the Bridge openlye, hee perſiſted in the ſame his confeſsion, confirming it to bee the trueth.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Giuen <date>the 26. of March 1582.</date> in the preſence of the vndernamed</dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>Zuerius</item>
                           <item>Blomart.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition_original">
               <head>An other Examination ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the 24 of the ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of March 1582.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEyendo el dicho Antonio de Venero (puesto ſobreiel atormentando) preguntado quien po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian mas hauer ſabido d'esta empreſa? Dize ningunos otros, que los por el aqui delante nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brados.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preguntado ſi d'esta impreſa no han ſabido Andres de la Maça Pedro d' Oroſco, Pedro de la Pen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a, o Valentin de Meurs? Dize que no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:36"/>
                  <hi>Pregu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tado ſi no ſe acuerda<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> (esta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do à la menſa del dicho An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>astro ſu amo ſe platicò y disputoſi era licito dematara ſu Excell. por zelo de la fee) el Clerigo Antonio Timmerman entonces declarò: que ſe podria hazer ſin pecado? Dize que d'ello no ſa acuerda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preguntado ſi no ſabia quien era el que estaua à Canallo iunto al Castillo quando el dicho efeto era complido? Dize que no.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yera dicho Examination firmada por los dichos Sennores Eſclauines</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. Zuerius. L. Blomaert.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition_translation">
               <p>THe ſaide <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Venero</hi> being vpon the racke examined what other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons might haue hadde intelligence of this enterpriſe, ſaieth, no other than thoſe whome he hath aforenamed.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether <hi>Andrew del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Maſſa, Peter</hi> of <hi>Oroſco, Peter della Penna,</hi> or <hi>Valentine de Meurs</hi> knew nothing of the ſaide enterprice, he ſaieth, No.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not that when ſome ſpéeche and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:1999:36"/>
paſſed at the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters table, whether for zeale of religion it were lawfull to ſlay his excellencie, the Monke <hi>Antony Timmerman</hi> didde then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that it might lawfully be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne. He ſaieth that he remembreth it not.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded whether he knoweth not who he was that was on horſebacke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Caſtle when the déede was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? he ſaith, No.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>This examination was conferred before the ſaide Lordes Shirifes,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Iohn Zuerius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lewes Bloemart.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>The Examination of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony Timmerman, taken in the preſence of the Lords, the Markgraue, Godfrey Montens, M. Iames Zuerius, and Lewis Bloemart, Shirifes of the towne of Antwerpe the 18. 19. and 23. day of March. 1582.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANtony Timmerman</hi> born in <hi>Dunkirke</hi> of the age of one and thirtie yeares, ſometimes Monke of the order of the white Friers, hauing his Chamber in the
<pb facs="tcp:1999:37"/>
long Newſtréete at the golden Horſe.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded what acquaintance he hath in the houſe of <hi>Iaſper Annaſtro,</hi> ſayeth that diuers times he hath ſaid Maſſe in the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> alſo that he hath ſent others thither for the ſame purpoſe, &amp; that therefore he had his finding as Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leine to the Spaniſh Nation, and that the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> paide him.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded what priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication he hathe had with one <hi>Iohn Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> a Spaniard of <hi>Biſcay</hi> in the houſe of the ſayde <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> ſaith, that the ſaide <hi>Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Friday laſt came to him to ſhrift, deſiring alſo to receiue the Sacrament at his hande, which he miniſtred vnto him, for the which the ſaid party gaue him two dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Piſtolets of gold, deſiring the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour to pray for him. Alſo that according to the deſcription of his ſtature and apparel that he ware, it ſéemeth to be the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who vppon Sundaye at noone diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a Dagge againſte his excellencies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, what the ſaide <hi>Iaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy</hi> gaue him to vnderſtande concerning
<pb facs="tcp:1999:37"/>
this déede, either in his confeſſion, or before or after the ſame: alſo whether he did not ſhewe him what he was promiſed for the performance of that Act, ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Iaureguy</hi> did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe vnto him, that the ſaid <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro</hi> woulde him ſelfe haue done it, if he could not haue perſwaded him thereto: ſaying moreouer that he woulde execute the ſaide déede the ſame Fridaye at dinner, and that onlie for the glory of God, and becauſe his father being an olde man ſhould be reléeued.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, whether he told not the ſayd confeſſor in what place he was purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to doe this déede, &amp; with what weapons: ſayth, that he told him that he purpoſed to doe it at the table as he thought, but ſhewed him not with what weapons.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, whether the ſayd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor did finally abſolue the ſayd <hi>Iauregui,</hi> ſo as he might execute his pretended déede, which afterward he committed againſt the perſon of his excellencie: Confeſſeth that he abſolued the ſayde <hi>Iauregui</hi> in this manner: That if he did not execute it for lucre of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but onely for the glorye of God and of a
<pb facs="tcp:1999:38"/>
zeale to the Catholike Romane Religion, that then it was lawfull for him to doe it, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him therevpon abſolution, hauing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe before repreſented to his view all ſuche daungers as might ſpring forth of the ſayd déede.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, whether he enquired of <hi>Iareguy</hi> if any other were able to vtter the pretence of the execution of the ſayd déede: ſayth, that he ſhewed him that no man was able to ſay any thing thereof, but onely the ſaid <hi>Iaſper Annaſtro, Antony</hi> of <hi>Venero,</hi> and an other man a <hi>Spanyard,</hi> whome he named not, either by name or ſurname: but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide Confeſſor geſſeth that it was a young man, whome he had often ſéene aboute the ſame time comming and going to the ſame houſe: the ſaide young man being reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tall of ſtature, with a blacke bearde cut after the Spaniſhe maner, of a browne pale colour, long and leaue viſaged, aboute <hi>24.</hi> or <hi>25.</hi> yeares of age, as it ſéemed, wearing ordinarily a Spaniſh Caſſock of a gray ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, and a blacke cloake.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, what ſpéech paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the ſaide Confeſſor and the ſaid <hi>Iaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:38"/>
of <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> touching this déed commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt his Excellencie, ſaieth, that the ſayde <hi>Annaſtro</hi> neuer ſpake any thing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, either in Shrifte, or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, whether the ſaide <hi>Iaureguy</hi> ſhewed him not, that <hi>Valentine de Meurs, Anthony Waechmans,</hi> and <hi>Anna Haecht,</hi> ſeruantes in the ſaide <hi>Annaſtroes</hi> houſe, knewe nothing of the practiſe or effecte of the ſaide déede attempted againſte his excellencie, ſaieth, that the perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed, knewe nothing thereof as the ſaid <hi>Iaureguy</hi> tolde him, and declared in his confeſſion.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, whether the ſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro, Iaureguy</hi> or <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Venero,</hi> ſaid not vnto him, that the King hadde by <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Yſunça</hi> made greate promiſes to the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> for the performing of the déede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Excellencie, ſaith, that he neuer knew or heard that of any body.</p>
               <p>Being demaunded, whether he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor hathe not aforetime bene in the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> when ſitting at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he was demaunded, whether it were lawfull for any manne without offence, to
<pb facs="tcp:1999:39"/>
ſlaye his excellencie: what aunſweare was made thereto, when it was, and who were there preſent, declareth, that the ſaide <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtro</hi> hath ſundrie times moued that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to him: &amp; namely at the table in din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner time, or ſo ſoone as the Table was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, either the firſte or ſeconde Saterday before Candlemaſſe, &amp; that there were then preſent <hi>Andrew de la Maça, Antony</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero,</hi> and <hi>Valentine de Meurs:</hi> and that hée this Confeſſor anſwered, that no particular or priuate perſon mighte doe it, but that it pertained onely to the Iuſtice. Whereto the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> (as he remembreth) replied, that the King being a publike perſon might commaund an other to doe it: wherevppon this Confeſſor ſaide, that it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man with money to buy an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers life. He declared farther, that about fouretéene dayes ſince, he the ſaide Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour being at the Table, or elſe ſoone after they were riſen, hearde the ſaide <hi>Annaſtro</hi> vſe theſe or ſuch like wordes: <hi>Valla me dios no at en esta tierra Flamenco que ſe atreua à este Principe de Oranges?</hi> whereto he the ſayde Confeſſor replied, ſaying: <hi>Los Flamencos no
<pb facs="tcp:1999:39"/>
ſon tan furioſos como vos otros,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Maça</hi> was not then preſent, but was depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Confeſſion being read before the ſaid Confeſſour vppon the Bridge of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, vnder the open eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he being loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and vndone, he perſiſted in the ſame in the preſence of the Shirifes this <hi>26.</hi> of March <hi>1582.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Subſcribed <hi>Zuerius,</hi> &amp; <hi>L. Bloemart.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <head>Here enſue the Copies of the Letters, vvritten by the ſaide <hi>Annastro,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Parma, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="letter_original">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sennor Hermanno.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DE Brujas os eſcreui ayer, y aura dos horas que llegue aqui, y no he podido hallar à Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro de Cubiaur, ni ſaber d'el, mas de que vn maestro dize, que paſſo de Doura à Cales ocho
<pb facs="tcp:1999:40"/>
dias a vn hombre caſi de ſus ſennas. Yo paſſó de mala gana à Cales, por el tiempo que pierdo en boluer a caſa: y a demas esto, el viento es contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, y no podre partir oy, pero ſera mannana Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bado plazie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do à Dios, Al ſennor Antonio Espin. nola beſo las manos, y que tengo gana deboluerme Al ſennor Andres de la Maça beſo ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bien las manos. Yo os encomiendo que tengays cuenta de lo que haz que hazer hasta que yo buelua: de papeles y aſſignaciones como de lo demas, que yo me dare laprieſſa que pudiere. Pagareys luego à Hernando de Nagera las <hi>402.</hi> libras que Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſar de Burgos eſcriuió ſe le dieſſen, porque de Cales le tengo de eſcreuir que estan pagadas, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bialde quita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ça dello. A <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentin me encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo, y à Iaureguy dezid que os ayude en lo de la eſcritura, y nuestro Sennor, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>En Dunquerch. <date>
                        <hi>16.</hi> de Março. <hi>1582.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>El ſubſcripto era</hi> Vuestro hermano Annastro</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>El ſobreſcripto era.</hi> Al Sennor Antonio de Venero mi hermano Anuers.</trailer>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Al porte <hi>4.</hi> Florins, dando lo a las ocho horas de la manana et lunes que es <hi>19.</hi> de Março.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="letter_translation">
               <pb facs="tcp:1999:40"/>
               <head>Annaſtros Letters written from Dunkirke.</head>
               <p>GOOD brother, yeſterday I wrote vnto you from <hi>Bruges,</hi> and I arriued heere two hours ſince, but cannot yet finde <hi>M. Peter</hi> of <hi>Cubiaur,</hi> either heare anie other newes of him: but that a maſter of a ſhip ſhewed me, that about eight daies ſince there was one like him that paſſed from <hi>Douer</hi> to <hi>Callis.</hi> Very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing I am to goe to <hi>Callis</hi> leaſt loſing my time I ſhal not come ſoone inough home. Beſides the wind being contrarie I cannot depart this day, but to morrow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saterday, if it pleaſe God I ſhall. I humbly greete maſter <hi>Anthonie Spinula</hi> &amp; am very deſirous to returne home. I alſo humbly greete <hi>Andrew Maſſa.</hi> I pray you ſet to your hand to any thing that is to be done before my returne, as well for writings and aſsignations, as for any other matter. For my part I will make as much haſt as I may. You ſhall preſently pay <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gera</hi> the 402. pounds that <hi>Baltaſſar</hi> of <hi>Burgos</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be deliuered him: for from <hi>Callais</hi> I will write that they be paid. And ſend him the acquaintaunce. I commend me to <hi>Valentine,</hi> and will <hi>Iaureguy</hi> to helpe you in your writings. Our Lord, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At <hi>Dunkirck</hi> 
                     <date>this 16. of March 1582.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>The ſubſcription was.</hi> Your brother Annaſtro.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>The ſuperſcription was.</hi> To my brother Anthony of Venero. <hi>At Antwerpe.</hi>
               </trailer>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>To the Poſt. 4. Florins ſo that he deliuer them vpon Munday at 8. a clocke in the morning, which ſhall bee the 19. of March.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter_original">
               <pb facs="tcp:1999:41"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SENNOR.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>PARA</hi> pagar a Baltaſar de Burgos las qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro cientas y dos libras, no hallo otro remedio, por la breuedad d'el tiempo ſino dezir a Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando de Nagera que tenia yo orden del dico Burgos: para que ſe dieſſen a el dichas quatro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientas y dos libras, y que ſe las querays pagar luego, y que Valentin ſe las dé, y quital de luego dos quitanças vna copia de otra, en que diga que ſe las days por orden de Baltaſar de Burgos, y que ſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liga a hazer las buenas al dicho Baltaſar de Bura gos, y d'esta manera el dicho Burgos ſe podra va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler dellas con ſu commodidad. Hazelde luego a la hora que esta recibays, antes que ſe haga el em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleo: porque de otra manera no veo orden de que vengan a mannos d'el dicho. Y aſſi os ruego mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho que esto ſe haga luego el miſmo Lunes. Dira Nagera, que no tiene auiſo: direyſle vos, que es hombre trabaioſo, y que no quereys aguardar a eſſo, porque yo os lo ordiné aſſi, y Burgos esta deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueydo de dineros. En el empleo me parece bien lo que ay le eſcreui de Brujas, que ſe haga de la mercaderia que pide Diego Carreno, prouando la primero algunas vezes, y al tiempo del effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto ponerſe vna medida, y dos rodondas:
<pb facs="tcp:1999:41"/>
y d'esta manera comparà con mas ſeguridad, y menos ambaraç<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: y para aquel vestido tomarle la medida por detras. Esto tengo por mejor que lo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro, y de menos embaraço, y mas ſeguro: y ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bien puede ponerſe lo otro, para en caſo de neceſſidad. Penſad en ello, y mirad qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to va en que el empleo ſeacierte Hazed cuenta, que yo me detendre en Cales el Sabado por todo el dia, para eſcreuit à <hi>Apodaca,</hi> y despachar le correo, y despues he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nester tres dias para aſſentar mi cuenta con aquel hombre, y dezirle lo que conuiene, porque vaya to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do per orde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: y despues ſe podra hazer quando el corredo quiſiere, y dezilde que le de Dios buena dicha, y que conſideres bien lo mucho que importa que el empleo ſea bueno.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>En la margen eſt aua eſcripto.</p>
                  <p>Otra vez torno à dez ir lo de Nagera, porque Baltaſar de Burgos esta falto de dineros, y embi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alde luego la vna cedula del dicho Nagera, y por esto doy esta ventaja de 13¼ libras. A Valentin y Iaureguy me en comiendo mucho.</p>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>El ſobre ſcripto era: <hi>Para Antonio de Venero.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter_translation">
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:42"/>SIr I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finde by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſhortneſſe of the time no other remedie how to pay <hi>Baltaſſar</hi> of <hi>Burgos</hi> the 402. pounds, but to ſhew <hi>Ferdinande</hi> of <hi>Nagera,</hi> that I had commiſsion from the ſaid <hi>Burgos</hi> to deliuer him the ſaid. 402. pounds, and that you will preſently pay him: and let <hi>Valentine</hi> pay him the mony, taking of him two acquittaunces, the one copied out of the other, wherin he muſt confeſſe that you doe deliuer the ſame vnto him by the appointment of <hi>Baltaſſar</hi> of <hi>Burgos,</hi> then binde him to make them good to the ſaid <hi>Baltaſſar</hi> of <hi>Burgos,</hi> and ſo may <hi>Burgos</hi> helpe himſelfe to his owne commoditie. Doe this immediatly, and euen ſo ſoone as you haue receiued theſe preſents, before the matter be performed, for I ſee no other meanes how they may come to his hands, wherefore I praye you heartelye let this be done this preſent Munday. <hi>Nagera</hi> will ſay that he hath no ſuch warrant: then ſhall you aunſwere him that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is troubleſome, &amp; that you wil not ſtay for that, ſeeing I haue ſo commaunded you, and that <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos</hi> is deſtitute of money.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>der this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>andiſe he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>neth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſtol, pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and tvvo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llets, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ervvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> L. Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>oulde be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> It ſeemeth good to mee the exploit and matter were performed, in ſuch ſort as ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday I wrote from <hi>Bruges,</hi> and that with ſuch Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundiſe as <hi>Diego Carreno</hi> requireth, hauing firſt tried it ſundrie times: and at the time of the execution ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to giue it a good meaſure, &amp; two rounds: &amp; in this wiſe it may be the more ſurely bought, and performed with leſſe hinderaunce. As for the garment, you muſt take meaſure behinde. I thinke this a better waye than the other, of leſſe hinderaunce, and moſte ſafe. Alſo for further aſſuraunce, the other<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dagger.</note> may be added for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsities ſake. Conſider heereof and marke of what importaunce the execution of this exploit is. Make your account that I will ſtay at <hi>Callais</hi> all Saterdaye,
<pb facs="tcp:1999:42"/>
there to write to <hi>Apodaca,</hi> &amp; to diſpatch the poſt. And afterward I ſhall neede three daies to make vp my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with this man: Tell him alſo what is needfull to be done, that all things may proceede orderlye, after which the matter may be diſpatched, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<note place="margin">He meaneth Iaureguy.</note> Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er will, and tell him alſo that I pray God graunt him good ſucceſſe, and that I would haue him marke howe neceſſarie it is that this exploit be performed.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>In the Margent was written.</p>
                  <p>Once againe I ſpeake to you of <hi>Nagera.</hi> For <hi>Baltaſar</hi> of <hi>Burgos</hi> needeth money: ſende therefore to him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly one of <hi>Nagera</hi> his Letters: for this I giue him the intereſt of 13. lib. 4. ſ. I commend me heartelye to <hi>Valentine</hi> and to <hi>Iauregui.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>The ſuperſcription was.</hi> For Antonie of Venero.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter_original">
               <head>Other Letters of the ſaid Annaſtro. <hi>Sennor hermano</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DE Bruias y de Dunquerch os eſcreui, yo me detuue en Dunquerch dos dias, bien deſgu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtado, por ſer el tiempo ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuerte y contrario que non pude paſſar: y aſſi me a conceſejo el go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernador de Dunquerch que paſſaſſe portierra, y que era mejor: y aſſi me robo el vn paſſa porte de Grauelinguas, y aqui, dos horas ha, en esta villa de Grauelingas, y mannana me yre por agua à Cales, à lo que entiendo, porque de aqui a Cales por tier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra esta todo ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no de Franceſes, que roban los que paſſam, y mas hara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſiendos Espa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>noles. Ha me di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho
<pb facs="tcp:1999:43"/>
vn tal Quadra que està aqui, que Pedro de çubiaur estuuo aqui quatro dias ha, y que enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diò que era y do a Cales, podra ſerque alli le halla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, entre ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to hazelos lo meior que pudieredes. Y eſſe empleo de las mercaderias ſe puede hazer a cada hora, y ſea tan bueno que los duonnos no ſe quexen. No tengo mas que eſcriuir, Nuestro Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp;c. En comiendome a Valentin y Iaureguy. Al ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor Marça beſo las manos, y Nueſtro Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor, &amp;c. En Grauelingas <hi>17.</hi> de Março <hi>1582.</hi> Harta ventura ha ſido aner eſcapado en el camino, legu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> andan los Franceſes. Yo ſere alla lo mas presto que pudiere, que ya queria ſer buelto.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>El ſubſcripto Era. <hi>Veſtro buen hermano Annaſtro.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter_translation">
               <head>Other Letters of the ſaid Annastro.</head>
               <p>MY Lorde and brother I writ vnto you from <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> and <hi>Dunkirke.</hi> Two daies I abode at <hi>Dunkirke</hi> though farre againſt my minde, becauſe the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſo rough and contrarie that I could not paſſe: wherefore the gouernour of <hi>Dunkirke</hi> counſailed mee to goe by land (as the better way) and ſo he made mee a paſport for <hi>Graueling,</hi> whether I came two houres ſince, from whence I will to morrow depart by water; (as I thinke) to <hi>Callais,</hi> for that betweene this &amp; <hi>Callais</hi> the waies be peſtered with French men that doe robbe the paſſengers, wherevnto they would bee more readie if they ſhould meete with any Spaniards. A certaine Quadra that is heere tolde me that <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Cubiaur,</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1999:43"/>
was taken foure daies agoe, and that he heard that hee was gone to <hi>Callais,</hi> it may bee that I maye finde hym there. In the meane time doe the beſt you can concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the exploit of merchaundiſe, it may be done at al times, and let it be ſo well done, that the maſters finde no fault. I haue no more to write. But our Lord, &amp;c. commend me to <hi>Valentine</hi> and <hi>Iauregui.</hi> I humbly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the Lord Maſſa. Our Lord, &amp;c. From <hi>Graueling</hi> this 17 of March 1582. It was a great chaunce that I eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped all the waye, the Frenche doe ſo range vp and downe. I will be there ſo ſoone as I may, for I would with a good will be at home alreadie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>The ſubſcription was,</hi> Your good brother Annaſtro. <hi>After the which was written,</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Giue this Poſt whoſe name is Coppenhaghen that which is written vpon the Letter, for guiding me hither.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>His excellencies letters vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with his owne hande.</head>
               <div type="letter">
                  <p>MY L. of <hi>Aldegond,</hi> I heare that to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the ij. priſoners, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plices that ſhot at me, ſhall be executed. For my
<pb facs="tcp:1999:44"/>
owne parte I doe willingly forgiue them whatſoeuer they may haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded againſt me: and if peraduenture they haue deſerued ſome ſore and ſharpe puniſhment, yet be a meane to my Lordes the Magiſtrates not to ſuffer them to abide any great torment. But rather if they haue ſo deſerued, to content themſelues with ſome ſpeedie death. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I bidde you good night.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your very good friend to do you ſeruice,</hi> William <hi>of</hi> Naſſau.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Done in the priſon of the tovvne of Antwerp in the preſence of my Lordes, Leſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, M. Iames Zuerius, and Lewis Bloemart Shirifes, <date>the 28. of March. 1582.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MAiſter <hi>Anthonie Timmerman</hi> priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, readie to receyue his death wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto he was yeſterdaye before noone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the <hi>Vierſchale</hi> by the Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters and Shirifes of this towne, ſaith and declareth in forme following.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, he ſayth, that hauing better cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:1999:44"/>
that whiche was ſpoken at the table in the houſe of <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annaſtro,</hi> when the ſaide deponent dined there, the ſaid <hi>Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro</hi> propounded and argued: Whether by vertue of the proſcription whiche the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hathe publiſhed, anye man maye lawfullye ſlaie his excellencies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in trueth he cannot ſaye whether <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Naſſa</hi> were preſent or not, either thys ſpéeche paſſed aboute the ende or after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, adding moreouer, that he is well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and certaine, that <hi>Valentine</hi> of <hi>Meurs</hi> ſate at the Table that dinner, but was then gone awaye. Moreouer the ſaide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned perſon acknowledgeth his great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight and error whiche he helde, in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that by vertue of the ſaide proſcription it was lawfull to ſlay his excellencies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Being therefore now better informed by learned men concerning the ſaide opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hauing further conſidered of the matter, he doeth by this preſente reuoke the ſame. Wherefore he requeſteth the Lordes Magiſtrates of this Towne to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him hys ſayde offence alſo to adde this to his former confeſſion, and if the
<pb facs="tcp:1999:45"/>
other be publiſhed, to publiſh this withal, to the end no man thinke that he dyed in ſo wicked an opinion.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Subſcribed. <hi>Zuerius.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Prince of Parma his Letters.</hi> Alexander Prince of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma and Plaiſance, Lieuetenaunt, Gouernour, and Captayne Generall.</head>
               <div type="letter">
                  <p>RIght deare and welbeloued, woulde to God you knew as well as the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of theſe partes, with what zeale and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection I haue alwaies proceeded &amp; procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the weale, quiet and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quilitie of theſe countries generallie, wherof I ſeek no greter nor more euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimonie, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the paines that I haue taken, the dueties which I haue yeelded, and the perils and daungers whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch I haue incurred in ſeeking to reſtore the
<pb facs="tcp:1999:45"/>
whole to hir auncient brightneſſe and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, wherewith theſe Prouinces were wont to floriſh. According wherevnto, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vſed the death of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (the one and onely inſtrument and Author of ſo many miſeries and calamities whiche you haue endured) as a meane to open the way vnto you, I hope he hath likewiſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from before your eies the vaile, which ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and kept you from knowing, or more neerely conſidering the ſleightes, ſuttleties, and inuentions, wherewith the ſaide Prince nouriſhed your miſtruſts, and through hys owne couetouſneſſe and ambition continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your miſeries, yea ſo farre foorth, that to the ſame ende he ſought to bring you into the ſubiection &amp; intollerable yoke of thoſe, from whom in former worlds you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſuch domages and enmities. Thus much I thought good to write vnto you, to thende to aduertiſe and aſſure you, that in caſe you wil preuaile in this occaſion and commoditie whiche God dothe offer vnto you, you ſhall not finde anye man in this worlde that will aide and aſsiſte you wyth more ſinceritie, readineſſe and affection, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1999:46"/>
I wil: offering vnto you to the ſame effect whatſoeuer I may by vertue of the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſpecial power vnto me giuen by his Maieſtie, of whome I am well aſſured that you ſhal reape no leſſe grace and fauor, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any worſe entertainement, than thoſe haue tried, who truſting wholly in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall clemencie wherewith hee is endued, haue willingly caſte themſelues into the armes of his royall curteſie and gentleneſſe. Wherevpon I will expecte your anſweare, which I pray God may bee ſuch as I deſire for your owne benefite and quietneſſe, alſo that it may bee ſo ſpeedily, that his Maieſtie may haue occaſion to deſiſte from ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration as he maketh for the atteyning to this ende, by ſome other meanes peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more violent and vnprofitable to your ſelues. Thus right deere and welbeloued, God haue you in his holy and worthy kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Tournay</hi> 
                        <date>this 25. of March 1582.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Subſcribed, <hi>Alexander:</hi> And ſomewhat lower <hi>F. Garnier.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1999:46"/>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>The Superſcription was,</p>
                     <p>To our right dere &amp; welbeloued, the Mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, Amptman, Borowmaiſters, Shirifes, Counſaile, and Rent maiſters of the Towne of <hi>Antwerp.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The like letters, <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched to the Inhabitantes of <hi>Bruxelles, Gaunt, Bruges, Ypres, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>Annaſtro his Letters written from <hi>Tournay.</hi> Muy mag. Sennor.</head>
               <div type="letter_original">
                  <p>PVes ha querido N<hi rend="sup">o.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">or</hi>. que el Principe de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range aya acabado ſus dias, ſe ha de creer que es para auer miſericordia de estas tierras que eſtauan affligidas, y yo estoy aggradado de auer ſido occaſione inſtrumento de ſa muerte, por el ſeruicio que deuo a mi Rey, y por la quietud y repoſo que deſſéo a los estados: y quando mi criado no fuera ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te para hazer lo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hizo, yo tenia determinae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o de matarle por mi mano, por ſaccat esta tierrae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l trauajo en que estaua. He querido eſcriuira
<pb facs="tcp:1999:47"/>
v.m. y al Sr. ſu hermano esta carta para aſſegurar los que pueden confiar en la miſericordia que ſu Mag. y ſu Alteza del Principe de Parma deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea hazer conlos de eſſa villa, ſin accordar ſe de las faltas paſſadas: ſi no con animo de perdonar las todas, y que todos puedan viuir pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. Y pues que v. m. tiene mano para po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der dar a entender à eſſos S. Ses. del magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do esta buena voluntad, y tomar buen conſejo en eſſe negocio, aſſegurando los que en lo que yo pudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere fauoreſcer los lo hare de muy buena gana. Y ſi quiſierem empleara v.m. en ello, y al So. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentío ſu hermano. y lleguarſe por aca, yo les em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biare paſſa porte de ſu Alteza aſſegurando los. Y ſaldre fiador por la ſeguridad de ſui perſonas, y respondan me de la voluntad que en esto tienen, y no ſe ofreſce otra coſa por agora N. S<hi rend="sup">or.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>de Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay <date>à <hi>25.</hi> de março, <hi>1582.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Beſa las manos a vos.</hi> 
                        <hi>mes.</hi> 
                        <hi>Gaſpar de Annaſtro.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter_translation">
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Noble Lordes,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SIth it hath pleaſed God to end the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his daies, you are to beleeue it to be, to the ende to ſhewe mercie to theſe Countries which were affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and I reioice that I was the occaſion and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his death, bothe for the duetie I owe to my
<pb facs="tcp:1999:47"/>
King, and for the reſte and tranquilitie of theſe eſtates. For if my ſeruant had not beene ſufficient to doe that whiche is done, my ſelfe was reſolued with my owne hand to haue ſlain him, ſo to deliuer this countrie out of the trouble it was in. This Letter I thought good to write to you, &amp; to my L. your brother, to the end to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you that you may ſuerlie repoſe your ſelues in the mercie which his Maieſtie &amp;, the P. of <hi>Parma</hi> his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe deſire to ſhew to this town: as not to thinke vpon anie former faultes, otherwiſe than fullie to pardon them, ſo as, all men maie liue peaceably. Further, ſith it lieth in you to giue the Lordes and Magiſtrates to vnderſtande of this good will, alſo to take good aduice co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this affaire, aſſuring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that in what I may I will moſte willingly pleaſure them. If in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they will vſe you and your brother <hi>Laurence</hi> as meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers hither, I wil ſend you a paſſeport fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with all ſufficient aſſuraunce, and will my ſelfe remaine pledge for the ſuretie of your perſons. Let mee vnderſtande your willes herein. Thus not hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other thing at this preſent, our Lorde &amp;c. </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Tournay</hi> 
                        <date>this 25. of March. 1582.</date>
                        <hi>Subſcribed,</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>I humbly ſalute your Lordſhips,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Iaſper</hi> of <hi>Annastro.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>The Superſcription was this, To the noble Lordes <hi>Denis de Meurs,</hi> and <hi>Laurence de Meurs.</hi> At <hi>Gant.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:48"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for Thomas Charde and William Broome. <hi>Anno</hi> 1582.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1999:48"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
